<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-08T12:23:06-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andrew P. Dillon</title><subtitle>Poetry, blog posts, links, &amp; contact info for poet Andrew P. Dillon</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to Web Blog</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/howToWebBlog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Web Blog" /><published>2020-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/how-to-web-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/howToWebBlog">&lt;p&gt;I finally got the website up! I’m pretty proud of myself, because it’s my first website, and I figured out everything through trial &amp;amp; error and reading a LOT of help forums. Jekyll does provide a template for the website, but I had to learn enough HTML, CSS, &amp;amp; Liquid (the templating language Jekyll uses, developed by Shopify) to write &amp;amp; modify everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I kept getting a generic build error, so I ended up building the site locally with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt; command, and pushing the contents of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory (which is re-written each time you run the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;serve&lt;/code&gt; command) to my GitHub repo. I have to use a pretty manual/unsophisticated workflow to update the website for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, GH Pages isn’t handling the actual source code for the blog. It doesn’t have any effect on the website except for the fact that the javascript for my Google Analytics tracker gets stripped out. I doubt anyone’s looking at the site yet, but I do ultimately want to know who/where/when visits, so I have some more troubleshooting to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the website is up &amp;amp; mostly running, I’ve been finalizing poems, and even writing a few new ones. I haven’t been working on the code or design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone through the process of setting up a custom domain with GH Pages, I’m a bit worried about getting the book online. Tom Johnson’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://idratherbewriting.com/documentation-theme-jekyll/index.html&quot;&gt;doc for his Jekyll theme&lt;/a&gt; does include instructions for publishing, but it was also last updated in 2016. I ran into a few issues with this site—the default Jekyll theme—that I’m worried will loom over that project, which is much more customized, and includes some scripting that I don’t fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-buffalo-bills&quot;&gt;The Buffalo Bills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first season since the 90s when I feel like they’re legitimately as good as they look (unlike the flashes of the Losman/Edwards/Fitzpatrick years). Obviously my life will change in zero ways relative to the success or failure of a professional sports team, but it means… I dunno, something… to see Buffalo’s team playing well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a boring cliche to say that a team is the lifeblood/heartbeat/soul of a town, but people in Rust Belt towns like Buffalo really care about their distractions—myself included, despite trying to ignore games &amp;amp; whole seasons over the past two decades. Like other mid-sized cities, Buffalo is undergoing something of a renaissance right now; but I grew up in the aftermath of the steel &amp;amp; grain industry exodus. Having this team to celebrate means something. I don’t know if I buy into the idea of sports-as-community, but in a crowd of Bills fans, I would without question shotgun a Labatt and body slam a folding table.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><summary type="html">I finally got the website up! I’m pretty proud of myself, because it’s my first website, and I figured out everything through trial &amp;amp; error and reading a LOT of help forums. Jekyll does provide a template for the website, but I had to learn enough HTML, CSS, &amp;amp; Liquid (the templating language Jekyll uses, developed by Shopify) to write &amp;amp; modify everything.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog Songs</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/blogSongs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog Songs" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/blog-songs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/blogSongs">&lt;p&gt;So I didn’t keep track of my progress on the book. Or anything else this year. I guess who cares since I haven’t even launched this site yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve really only started working on the book in earnest since the beginning of November. I’m shifting focus now to launch my author’s website first. I’m not sure if I’ll continue posting about the book, but for now, here’s where things stand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the book is done, it’ll be located at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thegreatpermission.com&quot;&gt;thegreatpermission.com&lt;/a&gt;. I’m creating it on top of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://idratherbewriting.com/documentation-theme-jekyll/index.html&quot;&gt;Jekyll Doc Theme&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.idratherbewriting.com&quot;&gt;Tom Johnson&lt;/a&gt; built. I guess you would call it a webbook. As much as I do want a physical book to hold in my hands &amp;amp; even one day sign at my readings (!!!), the digital format allows so many opportunities for me as a writer and you as a reader:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;navigation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multimedia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interactivity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;metapoetics/glosses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was too interesting to pass up. So possibly no publisher will be interested in this format (how would you monetize it?), but I think that’s okay. I have a career outside poetry, and if I have to continue balancing my professional &amp;amp; creative endeavors to travel the artistic avenues I want, I’m prepared to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- TGP screenshot --&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  

    &lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;images/tgpInProgress.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the author's in-progress webbook manuscript, showing the navigation &amp;amp; menu items on a blank `About the author` page.&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 650px&quot; /&gt;
  

  &lt;figcaption&gt;The book, in progress.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to quit my corporate job to write poems and give readings and talk to other artists every week. So the webbook will have links to my &lt;a href=&quot;https:www.patreon.com/andrewpdillon&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https:www.paypal.me/andrewpdillon&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt; =D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the book comes from a quote by poet &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alicefrimanpoet.com&quot;&gt;Alice Friman&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not sure if it’s codified in a book or interview anywhere, but she visited the University of Tennessee when I was in the first semester of my MFA. &lt;q&gt;Poetry is the great permission&lt;/q&gt; is one of the many very quotable things she said during her craft talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of the book is mostly in place. There are several poems I want to finish or revise before I publish the website, and that’s probably the bulk of the remaining work. But I still have a bunch of items to check off before the site is done from a technical perspective; the biggest ones are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figure out the logic for previous &amp;amp; next buttons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build a dark theme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set up Google Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;previous/next&lt;/strong&gt; buttons are complicated because I’m not in any sense a web developer. I have that functionality here on the blog because it’s a built-in variable for posts. The doc theme that I’m using for the book uses a YAML file to define the TOC, and I want the previous/next logic to loop through that to spit out buttons. It’s definitely possible because there’s separate logic that loops through that same YAML to create the sidebar navigation, and Jekyll’s own doc does something similar with its tutorials. I just don’t know what the fuck I’m doing yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also color deficient (similar to colorblind), and color palettes mean nothing to me, so the dark theme will be weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asana.com&quot;&gt;Asana&lt;/a&gt; to manage the effort, which I like a LOT more than other project management tools I’ve used. I’ve been part of Corporate America for almost a decade now, so I’ve used most of the big ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate Git, but use it because it’s integral to Jekyll &amp;amp; GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-than-poetry&quot;&gt;Other than poetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work in the healthcare industry as a Technical Writer. I’m in Nashville, where healthcare is maybe the biggest industry in the city—yes, even larger than music or tourism. It’s a wonderful career for an introvert. I wouldn’t have the skillset to put together this blog, much less my book, without my career in TechCom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been studying Spanish since June 2018. I use Duolingo every day (with a 906 day streak as of Dec 16), and before the pandemic, I took group classes at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tfli.org&quot;&gt;Tennessee Language Center&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not fluent by any stretch, but if I spent a couple months in a Spanish-speaking community, I think I’d come out communicating effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Duolingo image --&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a class=&quot;no_icon&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; href=&quot;https://www.duolingo.com&quot;&gt;

    &lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;images/duolingoReview2020.png&quot; alt=&quot;The author's 2020 Duolingo statistics. He was in the top 2% of experience earners.&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption&gt;My 2020 Duolingo stats&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m from Buffalo. The Bills are having a great season, and I’m not saying I had anything to do with that, but as soon as I stopped believing in jinxes, the Pegulas hired Sean McDermott &amp;amp; Brandon Beane. ::shrug:: Even though my family has been in Nashville since I was nine, I still consider myself “from” Buffalo. I’ve encountered a lot of people who have different opinions about how I should identify in that regard. Which is fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of people also misspell my last name. It’s &lt;code&gt;D-I-L-L-O-N&lt;/code&gt;. No second “i”. As far as I know, “Dillion” has never been a surname anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay! That seems like a whole blog post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><summary type="html">So I didn’t keep track of my progress on the book. Or anything else this year. I guess who cares since I haven’t even launched this site yet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your Invitation to a Modest Blog</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/yourInvitationModestBreakfast" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Invitation to a Modest Blog" /><published>2020-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/your-invitation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/yourInvitationModestBreakfast">&lt;p&gt;I decided to start this blog to record my progress and keep notes &amp;amp; ideas as I build this Jekyll site. I don’t know much about YAML or SASS, and I’ve never used Liquid before. Once I get the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;site&lt;/a&gt; built, I might continue blogging about drafting new poems, reading/performing, publishing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partly, I think this blog will help keep me accountable. Mostly, I think it’ll be useful to articulate the issues I have using the tools &amp;amp; logic I’m trying to learn. For example, “site” in the previous paragraph should have been a link to the homepage of this site. But it didn’t work. ::shrug::&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal for this site is to serve as my author website, but I also have a second Jekyll instance that I’m using to write the manuscript for my first poetry collection. I’ll probably write here about my vision for that book, and my plans for compiling it using this toolset.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="helloWorld" /><summary type="html">I decided to start this blog to record my progress and keep notes &amp;amp; ideas as I build this Jekyll site. I don’t know much about YAML or SASS, and I’ve never used Liquid before. Once I get the site built, I might continue blogging about drafting new poems, reading/performing, publishing, etc.</summary></entry></feed>