<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-16T08:06:54-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andrew P. Dillon</title><subtitle>Poetry, blog posts, links, &amp; contact info for poet Andrew P. Dillon</subtitle><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Forgotten Dialect of the (Tattooed) Heart</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/forgotten-dialect-tattoo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Forgotten Dialect of the (Tattooed) Heart" /><published>2023-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/forgotten-dialect-tattoo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/forgotten-dialect-tattoo"><![CDATA[<p>I’m finally feeling settled enough to write. <!-- here -->I’ve been in Amsterdam for almost four months, which was mostly consumed with my frantic efforts to establish the basic things a person needs to exist in a place: apartment, utilities, bank, phone, transit card, etc.</p>

<p>All the important things are taken care of now! I’m sleeping &amp; eating well! I have waterproof outfits for my daily bike to the office! And soon my books will arrive on a barge (and all my other possessions too), and I can truly celebrate.</p>

<h2 id="new-day-new-blog">New day, new blog</h2>
<p>The big question, and one that’s kept me from updating since I arrived in Amsterdam, is—what is this blog now? I started it with the purpose of recording my progress learning Jekyll (its tools, languages, &amp; processes) and troubleshooting my way through <a href="/tgp">the booksite</a>. Now that <em>TGP</em> is complete, what do I center my posts around?</p>

<p>Well, I imagine this will become a sort of travelogue. …I know—American exploring Europe. Boring. Done to death. But I promise this won’t become a series of “X is different in Y-country than in America” posts; or, god forbid “Everything is better in Europe”. (Even though…) Actually, I envision these to be much more mundane observations; for example—</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-ut">
  <p><strong>Mudane observation</strong></p>
  <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houndstooth">Houndstooth</a> is really popular here. I don’t know that I’d ever seen anyone wear the pattern outside a tailgate on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third_Saturday_in_October">3rd Saturday in October</a>, but I see it on a skirt, purse, coat, scarf, or hat almost every day here.</p>
  <p>Seeing it outside the SEC context, I guess it is an attractive pattern. Though it’s interesting that it’s also almost exclusively worn by woman here too. Obviously a pattern can’t be gendered, but anecdotally I don’t see men wearing it anywhere (outside of, I assume, Alabama frat boys and Bear Bryant, who’s been dead for 40 years).</p>
</div>

<p>I also have a new Tech Writer job at a FinTech company. Our Doc team uses a <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/guide/docs-as-code">Docs-as-Code</a> approach and publishes through a static site generator called <a href="https://getgrav.org">Grav</a>; I’m familiar with a lot of that from maintaining this site and building <em>TGP</em>, but there are a lot of new concepts to learn that should eventually allow me to experiment with new features here.</p>

<p>And of course, I’ll still write about poetry, poems, and the Amsterdam arts scene I’m only just starting to explore.</p>

<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>Normally, stressful life events make it difficult—if not impossible—for me to write. But I suppose all the new experiences &amp; imagery have been too insistent for my poetic sensibilities to ignore. I’ve drafted several new poems since arriving, and they’re very good.</p>

<p>When I was an undergrad, <a href="http://www.arthursmithpoet.com">Art Smith</a> told our class of impressionable aspiring poets that (I’m paraphrasing) “a poet loses the lyric voice by 25 if he hasn’t developed it.” Which really scared me.</p>

<p>Even though I’m well past 25, Art’s voice creeps into my mind when I go a stretch without writing. Have I lost my voice? Can I create anything better than a pastiche of my favorite poets? I don’t believe writer’s block is a thing that exists, but I do believe you can lose the desire to write and the ability to be satisfied with your writing. Thankfully, neither is the case today.</p>

<h3 id="the-great-permission"><em>The Great Permission</em></h3>
<p>The booksite has been live for almost five months now. Notwithstanding my lack of skill in publicity &amp; promotion, I’m a bit disappointed with the book’s performance. Only 440 visitors in total, with about two-thirds coming in the first week.</p>

<p>Again, I did not know how to effectively get the booksite in front of the eyes of people who could have shared it with a wider audience. But I thought I knew enough writers &amp; editors who would be willing to click the <strong>Share</strong> button for a free collection. That didn’t happen. The same is true for my two-time alma mater, which ignored my submission for the departmental newsletter that routinely features the accomplishments of alumni. Goodreads won’t even list the book—not because it’s self-published, but because it’s a website. I already knew to temper my expectations, but I’m still frustrated at how it’s played out.</p>

<p>On the other hand, my friends, family, &amp; members of my community of Nashville writers did come through. They enthusiastically read &amp; shared the booksite, and attended or shouted out my final readings in Nashville. In a year of significant personal turmoil, my gratitude for them helped keep me going.</p>

<h3 id="i-dream-of-lost-vocabularies">I dream of lost vocabularies</h3>
<p>I’m finally scheduled to get the tattoo I’ve wanted for years! Back in Nashville, there’s a very popular watercolor artist whose books I couldn’t get on, three years in a row. After searching a bit here in Amsterdam, I found <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ink.by.nina">Nina</a>. We had our consultation last week, and I’m already scheduled for a revision and the actual session later this month.</p>

<p>The tattoo is <a href="/municipalWorks#tattoos">the one I mentioned last year</a>—a half-sleeve representing the final line of this poem:</p>

<!-- SS: "Forgotten Dialect" -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/forgottenDialect.png" alt="A photo of Jack Gilbert's 'The Forgotten Dialect of the Heart'" style="max-width: 80%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 80%">
Jack Gilbert's <cite class="poem">The Forgotten Dialect of the Heart</cite>, from <cite class="book">The Great Fires</cite>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It’ll be pulling double-duty as as a celebration of the completion of my book, and the transition to the new phase of my life in the Netherlands.</p>

<h2 id="the-netherlands">The Netherlands</h2>
<p>Several online sources (mostly Reddit) warned me to prepare for the grinding &amp; overbearing Dutch bureaucracy: long waits, lack of communication, errors.</p>

<p>Wrong. Entirely wrong.</p>

<p>All my interactions with the Dutch government &amp; my local municipality (the <em>gemeente</em>) have been quick &amp; easy. The government has a program called <a href="https://www.digid.nl/en">Dig<strong>iD</strong></a>—a digital method of identifying yourself. Instead of entering your national ID number, an <a href="https://oauth.net/">OAuth</a> mechanism connects you to a government database that verifies your identity. Dig<strong>iD</strong> allows you to manage a lot of bureaucratic matters online, like registering with your municipality, managing your pension, or applying for healthcare. Very convenient!</p>

<p>I also read an uncountable number of warnings about Dutch directness/rudeness. Again, what were those people talking about? Maybe I haven’t interacted with enough Dutch people (my company is very international), but at the most extreme, I would say that the Dutch are simply not passive or passive-aggressive communicators. When you ask their opinion, they’re honest; when you make a mistake, they tell you without dancing around it. And thank god! I guess this does contrast with a place like my most recent home in Nashville, where people can be quite indirect or underhanded in their communication.</p>

<p>Like pretty much everywhere you go in this world, the people here are very nice. I think it’s a bit silly when people say the citizens of a particular country are “friendly”, as though that distinguishes them in any way. Divorced from easy labels that group us into political, classist, national camps, I’ve always found that people everywhere in the world are wonderful.</p>

<h3 id="poets--writers">Poets &amp; Writers</h3>
<p>I haven’t made it out to many literary events yet, but have found a couple that feel like they’ll become home bases for me:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://labyrinthamsterdam.nl/events/open-mic-monday/">Labyrinth Open Mic Monday</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/bodyelectricpresents">BODY ELECTRIC</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve read or been told about a few others that I’m looking forward to checking out when I’m more comfortable in my routines. One thing that seems to be true of all these events is that they’re multi-genre. I haven’t found a poetry-specific open mic or reading. Which I think is <em>fantastic</em>. I’ve <a href="/lightAroundBlog#podcast">previously mentioned</a> Dana Gioia’s <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/unbound/poetry/gioia/gioia.htm">recommendations</a> for American poetry. Amsterdam is putting some of them into action as a standard. Artists of all disciplines come together to be absorbed in other work.</p>

<p>At BODY ELECTRIC, every event features some combination of poets, musicians, storytellers, comedians, painters, costume designers, or others. Labyrinth is primarily poets &amp; musicians, but just this week we had an American, in town visiting his sister, spontaneously take the stage to talk about realizing his lifelong dream of becoming a pilot. It was riveting. He was a natural storyteller, and would have been in equal company on The Moth Radio Hour.</p>

<h3 id="second-language-acquisition">Second language acquisition</h3>
<p>Becoming proficient in Dutch is my only goal this year. I achieved all my other goals in 2022. Right know I’m just maintaining my <a href="/now#languages">Duolingo streak</a>, but plan to hire a tutor on <a href="https://www.italki.com">iTalki</a>.</p>

<!-- SS: Duo 1700 -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/duolingoStreak1700.png" alt="Duolingo's owl mascot wreathed in flames with the caption '1700 day streak! Congrats on using Duolingo for 1700 days in a row!'" style="max-width: 50%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 50%"></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Honestly, I’m not sure if learning Dutch is worth all the time. I’m doing it because I love studying languages, and as a sign of respect for my new home. But the reality is everyone in Amsterdam speaks English, including everyone at my new company. I wonder sometimes if I should stick with Spanish. It would be more practical for travelling! At the very least, I’ll come back to it when I gain a certain level of Dutch proficiency.</p>

<h2 id="can-a-poetry-blog-examine-stale-pop-culture-does-it-change-the-dynamic-of-the-blog-what-if-we-as-readers-expected-an-author-to-touch-on-the-many-facets-of-a-life-in-their-work-maybe-the-well-worn-paths-remain-the-pillars-of-our-zeitgeist">Can a poetry blog examine stale pop culture? Does it change the dynamic of the blog? What if we as readers <em>expected</em> an author to touch on the many facets of a life in their work? Maybe the well worn paths remain the pillars of our zeitgeist.</h2>
<p>That’s me Carrie Bradshaw-ing the header. Over the summer, I needed a low-stakes series to play in the background while I zoned out on the couch. So I started watching <cite class="tv">Sex and the City</cite>, finishing a couple weeks ago. I was in high school &amp; college during the show’s run on HBO, but never had HBO or the interest. As a straight teenage boy, I couldn’t have enjoyed it back then anyway (masculinity was, if you can believe, <em>even more toxic</em> at the turn of the century).</p>

<p>I thought it was mostly fun, with fewer cringey moments due to outdated social attitudes than I expected. I came away with some <strong>extremely cold takes</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li>It’s tragic that Kim Cattrall (who was arguably the most talented actor in the series) never saw her character elevated beyond a woman who <em>weirdly</em> likes sex. In the second half of the final season, they gave her cancer to make up for this, but it didn’t compensate for the fact that Samantha basically looped through the same two storylines for six seasons &amp; two movies.</li>
  <li>I had a hard time settling on who was the worse person: Carrie or Charlotte. They’re both grossly judgmental, shallow people, with (to be blunt) nothing to really offer a friend or partner; and for most of the series, whoever spoke the most recent line is who I thought sucked the most.</li>
  <li>In the end, I settled on Carrie being the worst; Charlotte was a better friend, I think. Carrie was incapable of letting any situation center on any other person.</li>
  <li>What in the world did an intelligent, confident, accomplished man like Aleksandr Petrovsky see in Carrie Bradshaw? THERE IS NOTHING INTERESTING ABOUT HER.</li>
  <li>Carrie &amp; Big ending up together is perfect, because while they’re boring &amp; crappy in different ways, they magnitude of their boringness &amp; crappiness is equal. For similar reasons, Charlotte should have ended up with Trey. I don’t remember anything being wrong with Trey, he’s just a similarly vapid person, and Harry is entirely too good for Charlotte.</li>
  <li>What was happening with Miranda’s wardobe in s1? I can’t decide if the androgynous Bowie look was the show’s indecision about making her character gay at some point (conforming to a straight 90s person’s idea about gayness), or its inability to conceive of a wardrobe for a person who is both a woman <strong>and</strong> a lawyer.</li>
  <li>There weren’t nearly enough Stanford-Anthony scenes.</li>
  <li>I should have more to say about Big, but there’s nothing there. He’s literally just a human man doing a low-rent Cary Grant impression, in a suit &amp; hair only the early 2000s could have considered appealing.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m finally feeling settled enough to write.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Poor (Nashville) Scene Canticles</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/poorScene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Poor (Nashville) Scene Canticles" /><published>2022-09-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/poor-scene</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/poorScene"><![CDATA[<p>I’m trying to be intentional about my remaining time in the United States. Even though I’ve lived in Nashville most of my life, there are a lot of things I’ve never done.<!-- here --> This week, Sarah &amp; I visited the Country Music Hall of Fame, using the Nashville Public Library’s <a href="https://library.nashville.org/services/community-passports">Community Passports</a> program. Here are a few photos from our afternoon:</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned="" data-instgrm-permalink="https://www.instagram.com/p/CjGnWb8gVVj/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" data-instgrm-version="14" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);">
  <div style="padding:16px;">
<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CjGnWb8gVVj/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style=" background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;" target="_blank">         <div style=" display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;">
          <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;"></div>
          <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;">
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;"></div>
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;"></div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div style="padding: 19% 0;"></div>
         <div style="display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;">
          <svg width="50px" height="50px" viewBox="0 0 60 60" version="1.1" xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><g stroke="none" stroke-width="1" fill="none" fill-rule="evenodd"><g transform="translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)" fill="#000000"><g><path d="M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631"></path></g></g></g></svg>
        </div>
        <div style="padding-top: 8px;">
          <div style=" color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;">
View this post on Instagram
          </div>
        </div>
        <div style="padding: 12.5% 0;"></div>
         <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;">
          <div>
            <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);"></div>
            <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;"></div>
            <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);"></div>
          </div>
          <div style="margin-left: 8px;">
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;"></div>
            <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)"></div>
          </div>
          <div style="margin-left: auto;">
            <div style=" width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);"></div>
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);"></div>
            <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);"></div>
          </div>
        </div>
         <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;">
          <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;"></div>
          <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;"></div>
        </div>
</a>    <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CjGnWb8gVVj/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;" target="_blank">A post shared by Andrew P Dillon (@andrewdillonpoetry)</a></p>
  </div>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="//www.instagram.com/embed.js"></script>

<!-- Factory reset old Macbook: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8SwVX_Jh5jc -->

<h2 id="the-book">The book</h2>
<p>Is out. My gods it’s done. There were years I wondered if I’d ever follow through &amp; finish it in any form. When I got the repo served and the custom domain configured and it was finally online, I felt extremely hollow. Like my soul had been peeled away from me. I was exhausted and wanted to never look at those poems again. After a good night’s sleep, though, I was rejuvenated. Since then, it really feels like a literal weight was lifted, and I’m just so proud of myself for getting it done.</p>

<p>It’s so fascinating to me that, for a project in any domain, a certain level of constraint is actually generative. That was true for me here. If not for the impending move (and realization that I might not be able to refocus on the book again for months), I would not have <em><a href="/tgp">TGP</a></em> out in the world now. I’d probably still be finalizing line edits on a couple poems and tinkering with the navigation.</p>

<p>The concept of a Minimum Viable Product was extremely useful. It’s a business term I’ve <a href="/unincorporatedProblems#mvp">mentioned before</a>, but in this context it was actually a form of permission (in keeping with the overarching theme of the booksite itself.) I allowed myself to punt on a few non-essential elements (dark theme, a prettier picture gallery, search) in order to release an otherwise complete manuscript.</p>

<p>I have a new respect for anyone who finishes a book now. The stress was hollowing me out. Obviously I had more going on than <em><a href="/tgp">TGP</a></em>, but in the weeks &amp; days leading up to   <time datetime="20220921">September 21</time>
, I started losing my appetite &amp; weight (20 lbs!), my digestion was all fucked up and I had debilitating heartburn for a few days, and my hair even started thinning. Now that the booksite is out there and plans for the move are mostly finalized, most of that has fallen away.</p>

<h3 id="farewell-reading">Farewell reading</h3>
<p>Also on   <time datetime="20220921">September 21</time>
, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/americanolounge">Uncorked at Americano Lounge</a> hosted my Farewell-to-Nashville/Book Release reading. It went extremely well! Probably one of the best readings I’ve ever given. It was a full house, and the audience was so focused.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I don’t have any IG posts to link to here. Friends posted stories that night, which have of course disappeared in the week since. However, Christine Hall (more on her <a href="#christine-hall">below</a>) did catch me at my final visit to her show 11 days earlier (should start at 1:15:50):</p>
<figure>
  <iframe width="100%" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qKfhgiqBweQ?t=4590" title="Poetry in the Brew open mic livestream" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
  <figcaption>
Look at the stress turning my fivehead into a sixhead.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I also got this clip (in my Berlin outfit) from a   <time datetime="20220928">September 28</time>
 open mic at <a href="https://soulnashville.com">SOUL</a> where I’m fidgeting a whole lot:</p>
<figure>
  <video controls="" controlslist="nodownload" muted="" autoplay="false" width="100%" height="400"> <source src="audio/soulOpenMic_2022-09-28.mp4" /> Oops! Your browser doesn't support HTML video. </video>
  <figcaption>
Thanks to <a href="https://www.instagram.com/blackwidowpoet">Gina Carillo</a> for grabbing this!
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="gratitude">Gratitude</h3>
<p>In the wake of all this stress &amp; effort, I’m feeling an immense wave of gratitude for all the people who supported me, believed in me, or showed up for me. Many of my friends are not poets, but came to my readings or read my new publications anyway. A lot of gatekeepers in Knoxville or Nashville generously invited me into their spaces to watch or perform. Many, <strong>many</strong> educators poured time &amp; energy into me, and expected that I could become better than I was at that time in my life.</p>

<p>Writing the <a href="https://thegreatpermission.com/acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</a> page was probably the most rewarding single effort in the entire process of creating the booksite.</p>

<h3 id="publicity">Publicity</h3>
<p>So now I’m trying to get people to read the damn thing.</p>

<p>My friend <a href="https://reedsy.com/emily-keough">Emily Keough</a> works in book publicity, and talked me through some of the basics of promoting a book. I did some research, a SWOT analysis, identified reviewers, media opportunities, &amp; other potential avenues of exposure—all of which went out the window when I received my job offer in Amsterdam and I knew I’d be leaving in October.</p>

<p>The fact that the booksite is in the world means everything went right. I wouldn’t change a single thing. But I was already at a bit of a disadvantage as a relatively unknown poet self-publishing in a (surprisingly) untraversed medium. Trying to promote retroactively is not ideal, but I’m hoping that the no-cost &amp; persistent availability render most of that irrelevant.</p>

<p>One challenge I’m noticing as I query reviewers &amp; other media opportunities is that a strongish bias remains against self-published titles. On one hand, I understand that literally anyone can throw a Creative Commons license on anything they produce, and that a publisher dedicating resources to your work lends you some credibility.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I couldn’t have produced my book with a traditional publisher. There’s no model for a booksite because there don’t seem to be any others. I couldn’t find any comp titles. It being open source, exclusively digital, freely available, &amp; PWYW, how would a publisher make any money? (<em>do</em> small publishers make money?) The closest thing I could find is <a href="https://pressbooks.com">Pressbooks</a>, which has a similar layout &amp; open-source backbone. But they focus on educational resources, and each time I’ve searched their catalog, I’ve found no creative titles. There are no poetry collections, and only a couple dozen of the 2000+ books are at all related to poetry (mostly as textbooks). Even those books that contain poetry are not presenting it in a way that leverages the web or web technology—all are either iframes of static poems or unstyled text undifferentiated from the surrounding content.</p>

<h3 id="concerns">Concerns</h3>
<p>Everything about publishing is new to me, so I’m mostly just keeping my head above water. Here’s what I’m most concerned about now that the booksite is done:</p>

<h4 id="will-anyone-read-my-book">Will anyone read my book?</h4>
<p>I’ve read social media from other authors who have basically said, “Be prepared for the harsh reality that your friends &amp; family will not buy your book”. In my case, of course, they won’t have to spend any money. But will they bother to read it? I think many of them will, yes. I have a tight group of supportive friends. As of this posting, Google Analytics tells me about 300 people have visited <em><a href="/tgp">TGP</a></em>. I don’t, however, expect that anyone will spend money on my book.</p>

<p>Right now, I have no plans for my next project, but I’m already unsure about devoting the effort I put into this collection for zero compensation. I don’t create for money, but it’s hard to create in a crushing capitalist hellscape without getting something back.</p>

<h4 id="creative-commons-implications">Creative commons implications</h4>
<p>I did a lot of reading to feel confident that I was applying <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/?ref=chooser-v1">the right license</a> and understood what it meant for future licensees. Still, it’s a lot of legalese—a domain where I have no professional experience. It’s also strange trying to specify what kind of reuse or adaptation is “allowed”, since that’s not really how art works. Artists have a reaction to other art and create without any real attribution all the time; though, I try to be very explicit about my influences at a granular level.</p>

<p>I don’t really expect copyright issues, but I do feel <strong>very strongly</strong> about the non-commercial aspect of the license I chose. If I’m not gonna make money here, I don’t want other folks to. Plus, now that I’ve applied the CC license, I can never revoke it.</p>

<p>Traveling an underutilized road here, and I’ll obviously blog about any updates in this regard.</p>

<h4 id="pwyw">PWYW</h4>
<p>Not so much a concern (since I don’t expect to make any money), but a few people have asked me about monetizing. Honestly, the pay-what-you-want model doesn’t feel like a risk at all. Based on my friends &amp; acquaintances who have published books, it seems like no one makes money on their book anyway; and if they make any money at all (especially as poets), it’s from paid readings. I <em>have</em> heard that book sales for academic settings (like creative writing classes) can be lucrative, but since I’m not open to producing a physical copy of <em><a href="/tgp">TGP</a></em>, that’s moot.</p>

<h2 id="this-blog">This blog</h2>
<p>A couple small updates on this website. <a href="/links">Links</a> now includes a subsection for published poems that didn’t make it into the manuscript. It’s mostly older poems from college or immediately after. I had planned to create a <strong>Read</strong> page for this, but since I already have <strong>Links</strong>, it didn’t make sense on rhetorical level to separate the two. I don’t love the current look, so I’ll probably tweak it later.</p>

<p>The homepage now calls out <em>The Great Permission: A reliquary</em> with some boilerplate text from my query letter. I also added my <a href="https://www.patreon.com/andrewpdillon">Patreon link</a> to the <strong>Contact</strong> callout.</p>

<p>Finally (and this was a total accident), the <strong>The Great Permission</strong> link in the header now points to <a href="https://www.thegreatpermission.com">thegreatpermission.com</a>. Coincidentally, when I initialized the new repository for the booksite, I named it <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/tgp</code>. I didn’t realize that this “baseurl” would get appended to my existing domain (andrewdillonpoetry.com). If I hadn’t purchased a domain for the booksite, the URL would be <em>andrewdillonpoetry.com/tgp</em>. However, I was already using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/tgp</code> as the permalink for the book promo page on this site, so now it just redirects to my book. Which is great!</p>

<h2 id="christine-hall">Christine Hall</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/xineraquel">Christine</a> is a legend on the Nashville poetry scene. She is the longtime host of <a href="https://poetryinthebrew.wordpress.com">Poetry in the Brew</a>, a monthly poetry-focused open mic that includes a feature. Some folks who have featured for PitB under Christine’s stewardship include:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/theconstantpoet">Michelle Awad</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://destinybirdsong.com/">Destiny Birdsong</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.tianaclark.com">Tiana Clark</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://kendradecolo.com">Kendra DeColo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.musicvf.com/songs.php?page=artist&amp;artist=Billy+Henderson&amp;tab=songaswriterchartstab">Billy Henderson</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.anandalima.com">Ananda Lima</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/mamaspeaks._">MAMA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://cionarousepoetry.com">Ciona Rouse</a></li>
  <li>yours truly <em class="fas fa-smile-beam"></em></li>
</ul>

<p>Christine is ending Poetry in the Brew after November’s event to reclaim that time and focus on her own personal/artistic endeavors. PitB has been at Portland Brew East since 2011, and Christine has hosted since 2014; before that (if I have my history right), it went by a different name at Windows on the Cumberland—a venue that shuttered so long ago, I doubt 10% of Nashville’s current residents would know the name.</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned="" data-instgrm-permalink="https://www.instagram.com/p/Ce7soGWs1vO/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" data-instgrm-version="14" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);">
  <div style="padding:16px;">
<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Ce7soGWs1vO/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style=" background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;" target="_blank">         <div style=" display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;">
          <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;"></div>
          <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;">
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;"></div>
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;"></div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div style="padding: 19% 0;"></div>
         <div style="display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;">
          <svg width="50px" height="50px" viewBox="0 0 60 60" version="1.1" xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><g stroke="none" stroke-width="1" fill="none" fill-rule="evenodd"><g transform="translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)" fill="#000000"><g><path d="M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631"></path></g></g></g></svg>
        </div>
        <div style="padding-top: 8px;">
          <div style=" color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;">
View this post on Instagram
          </div>
        </div>
        <div style="padding: 12.5% 0;"></div>
         <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;">
          <div>
            <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);"></div>
            <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;"></div>
            <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);"></div>
          </div>
          <div style="margin-left: 8px;">
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;"></div>
            <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)"></div>
          </div>
          <div style="margin-left: auto;">
            <div style=" width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);"></div>
            <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);"></div>
            <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);"></div>
          </div>
        </div>
         <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;">
          <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;"></div>
          <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;"></div>
        </div>
</a>    <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Ce7soGWs1vO/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;" target="_blank">A post shared by Christine Hall (@xineraquel)</a></p>
  </div>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="//www.instagram.com/embed.js"></script>

<p>If you’re on Nashville’s arts scene in any capacity, you probably know Christine at least by reputation. She has been a ceaseless &amp; enthusiastic advocate for art, anticapitalism, &amp; social justice. She’s the best kind of gatekeeper—welcoming one &amp; all (unless you’re a shithead) into the spaces she controls, while enthusiastically promoting all forms &amp; genres of poetry, from artists at all stages in their career. She’s the kind of literary citizen I’d aspire to be if I had half her dedication. I can’t adequately express my gratitude for her support these past six years (since I moved back to Nashville). She brought me into Nashville’s literary scene, and pointed me in all the right directions.</p>

<p>For more about Christine, read this <a href="https://nashvillevoyager.com/interview/daily-inspiration-meet-christine-hall">short interview</a> she did with <em>Nashville Voyager</em> in August 2021.</p>

<p>Thank you, Christine; and good luck! I can’t wait to see what you do next.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m trying to be intentional about my remaining time in the United States. Even though I’ve lived in Nashville most of my life, there are a lot of things I’ve never done.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Abridged History of Treason</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/abridgedHistory" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Abridged History of Treason" /><published>2022-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/abridged-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/abridgedHistory"><![CDATA[<p>The Republican Party has overthrown the United States government.<!-- here --> Or, more accurately, they’ve been overthrowing it for decades.</p>

<h2 id="minority-rule">Minority rule</h2>
<p>I was a high school sophomore when SCOTUS handed the presidency to George W. Bush, who lost the vote. Trump lost by a near-historic margin to Hillary Clinton, arguably the most qualified candidate in my lifetime. Both Republicans took office because of the <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/electoral-colleges-racist-origins">racist Electoral College</a>, which was designed to empower white Southern voters.</p>

<p>Before, during, &amp; since, all manner of voter suppression has been in play:</p>
<ul>
  <li>gerrymandering</li>
  <li>closed polling stations in urban areas</li>
  <li>reduced voting hours</li>
  <li>voter ID requirements</li>
  <li>disenfranchising felons</li>
  <li>purged voter rolls</li>
  <li>reduced or eliminated early voting</li>
  <li>physical intimidation</li>
</ul>

<p>Among others. Fast forward to the present—SCOTUS has overturned 50 years of legal precedent to allow states to force births, but won’t allow states to restrict the sale of certain types of guns. They’ve also appointed themselves legislators in their <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/06/30/1103595898/supreme-court-epa-climate-change">EPA ruling</a> that unwinds a law established by Congress—after, again, being established for 50+ years.</p>

<p>And mostly, liberals have ignored all of this. Progressives have been screaming &amp; waving their arms, but of course neoliberals on both sides view progressives as communists. Understand that when I mention progressivism in America, I’m talking about a centrist political position in the global context. American progressives want things like:</p>
<ul>
  <li>automatic voter registration</li>
  <li>universal healthcare</li>
  <li>guaranteed parental leave</li>
  <li>free or affordable higher education</li>
</ul>

<p>—all things that pretty much every other democratic nation instituted generations ago. Of course, you could argue that America is not a democracy anymore. I would agree. I’d go further and say that it’s also not a free country:</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-default">
  <p>If the cowardice of the political minority is legislated upon the entire populace, you don't live in a free country.</p>
  <p>If the state can overrule your decisions about your body, you don't live in a free country.</p>
  <p>If the state can <a href="https://time.com/5882735/tennesee-law-protest-voting-rights-felony/" target="_blank">arrest you for peacefully protesting</a>, you don't live in a free country.</p>
  <p>If the state can <a href="https://kfor.com/news/arizona-to-outlaw-recording-police-within-8-feet/" target="_blank">arrest you for recording police</a>, you don't live in a free country.</p>
  <p>If the state <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kids_for_cash_scandal" target="_blank">jails children to fund private prisons</a>, you don't live in a free country.</p>
  <p>And <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/rise-legislative-anti-democracy" target="_blank">on</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/13/briefing/anti-democratic-movement-us-politics.html" target="_blank">on</a>.</p>
</div>

<p>Remember that, of the 6 conservative justices, only Clarence Thomas was appointed by a president who the people chose. The current court should be 8-1 in favor of liberals. Which makes total sense because <em>most of the country is pretty liberal</em>. Presidential candidates from the Democratic Party almost always win the vote. Democratic candidates for Senate consistently get 10,000,000 more votes than Republicans; in the current Senate, Democrat Senators represent <em>over 41,000,000 more Americans</em> than Republican Senators—almost 13% of the country. In a 50-50 Senate. When you poll Americans on individual issues, the “liberal” side is almost always the majority opinion; see:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/06/13/about-six-in-ten-americans-say-abortion-should-be-legal-in-all-or-most-cases-2/">abortion</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/04/16/americans-overwhelmingly-say-marijuana-should-be-legal-for-recreational-or-medical-use/">cannabis legalization</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2020/06/23/two-thirds-of-americans-think-government-should-do-more-on-climate/">climate emergency</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/numbers-show-americans-opinions-gun-control-measures/story?id=84995468">gun control</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2020/09/29/increasing-share-of-americans-favor-a-single-government-program-to-provide-health-care-coverage/">healthcare</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/1651/gay-lesbian-rights.aspx">LGBTQ+ rights</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/05/08/most-americans-want-to-limit-campaign-spending-say-big-donors-have-greater-political-influence/">money in politics</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve been whiplashing between stages of grief (since 2015, but most recently) since the overturning of Roe v. Wade was leaked in May. I’m angry or depressed or naively hopeful or numb. It feels like the first time I had my heart broken. I still vote in every local, state &amp; federal election (Nashville, next up is August 4th), but I don’t believe the ballot can fix what’s happened in America. I don’t believe in this country.</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>No real news on the dev side of the booksite. As I mention <a href="#jobs">below</a>, job hunting has taken up most of my last two months. However, I did <em>finally</em> complete a draft of my centerpiece poem. It only took 5.5 years, which, yes, is an objectively long time, but also not the longest it’s taken me to finish a poem in this collection (12 years).</p>

<p>With this crucial poem done, I can now send the manuscript for review. Of course, that presents a challenge with hosting, which I mentioned in <a href="/municipalWorks#the-booksite">the previous post</a>. This, I think, is a much more solvable issue than finishing a poem that doesn’t want to end.</p>

<h2 id="technology">Technology</h2>
<h3 id="brave-creators">Brave Creators</h3>
<p>If you check my <strong><a href="/now">Now</a></strong> page, you might have seen that I got this website (&amp; my GitHub profile) verified with <a href="https://creators.brave.com">Brave Creators</a>. Which basically just means you can tip me in Brave’s native token, Basic Attention Token (BAT). It’s one of my favorite crypto projects because it enables a simple method for fans to directly compensate creative people. My booksite will have a Pay-What-You-Want model, and I hope crypto will be a significant part of that.</p>

<!-- image: brave address bar -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/braveAddressBar.png" alt="A screenshot of the current website viewed in Brave Browser, with the Brave Rewards icon (a multi-colored triangle) clicked to reveal a dialog that allows you to tip the author using Brave's cryptocurrency, Basic Attention Token." style="max-width: 70%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 70%">
As usual, Jekyll made this more complicated than necessary.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>There are two methods for verifying:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Download a file and add it to your project repo</li>
  <li>Add a DNS (Domain Name System) record to the hosting service for your website</li>
</ul>

<p>The former sounds easier, but didn’t seem possible for a site hosted on GitHub. This is the error message I kept receiving from Brave:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Retry Verification<br />
Your website, andrewdillonpoetry.com, was not verified because we were redirected too many times to verify your domain.<br />
Please reduce the number of redirects.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The authors of other GH-hosted Jekyll websites have described their verification process, so I don’t understand why I couldn’t. In any case, I was able to verify using the other option. The steps will vary depending on your host, but the new DNS record should look like this:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Host name</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Type</strong></th>
      <th><strong>TTL</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Data</strong></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">TXT</code></td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1H</code></td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">brave-ledger-verification=0e5e9be6d9a40ff3da74315f3ba56e8sf2m5f9ec0a83c2040b78eb77543ab3582721ea</code></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><strong>Notes</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Leave <strong>Host name</strong> blank; verifications must point to the primary domain, not subdomains.</li>
  <li>Brave provides you the string to paste into the <strong>Data</strong> field.<br />
This field is formatted differently than the file you’d use (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">brave-rewards-verification.txt</code>) for the other verification method; you can’t copy &amp; paste the contents of a verification file into this field.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="learning">Learning</h3>
<p>Since I was forced into a job hunt, I decided I should spend part of my time on professional development. Some of that time has been learning JavaScript, but as a Technical Writer, it’s made the most sense to focus on learning API documentation.</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>pplication <strong>P</strong>rogramming <strong>I</strong>nterfaces allow two different programs to talk to each other. If you’ve ever checked out with PayPal on Amazon or eBay, you’ve interacted with an API. API doc is part of a larger trend in the technical communication industry toward documentation for an audience of developers. Devs might use an API to add functionality to their website or app so they don’t have to create it from scratch. In contrast, traditional techdoc focuses on the end user, and how to help them do something with—or understand—a product or service. Think of what pops up in an app when you press F1 or click <strong>Help</strong>.</p>

<p>Tom Johnson (the same author whose Jekyll theme I’m using to build the booksite) created a popular course called <em><a href="https://www.idratherbewriting.com/learnapidoc">Documenting APIs</a></em>. I powered through the first two sections, which were immediately useful for some of the technical assessments I had to complete as part of the hiring process. This new knowledge could also be useful for adding functionality to this site—say, a contact form.</p>

<h2 id="personal-stuff">Personal stuff</h2>
<p>For some reason, my parents receive mail addressed to me. They recently bought a new home that I’ve never lived in, so this is baffling. Have you heard of the Salesians? I had not. Here’s a card they sent me:
<!-- salesian remembrance card (sent to my parents' house) --></p>
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/andrewSalesianCard.png" alt="A card mailed to the author's parents' house, with the following text: 'Andrew Dillon will be remembered during a Special Mass to be celebrated on May 24, 2022 in Bethlehem by the Salesian Missionaries of Jesus the Adolescent Province. Fr. Gus Baek, S.D.B. Director'" style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
I suppose to the Catholics I am dead.<br />And center-aligned text? Gross. At least they spelled my last name right
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is weird, right? It seems like they think I’m dead, but also they addressed the card to me. Even weirder is how the hell do they know who I am? Salesians are a Catholic sect, and I did go to Catholic mass or Sunday school until I was old enough to say I didn’t believe literally anything I was told there, but that was over 20 years ago and in a different state. Is this some kind of misguided request for donations? I can’t find much info about this practice, so reach out if you have insight.</p>

<h3 id="jobs">Jobs</h3>
<p>As I’ve alluded to, I was recently laid off. After a big reorganization within the business unit at my company, they eliminated several positions, and mine was one. Not a big surprise, since I was a Technical Writer at a company without that position in their career architecture. I had a couple opportunities to transition to other internal positions, but they would have required me to refocus as more of a Business Analyst or Project Manager. Both of those sound like terrible fits for me, and I like tech writing, so I decided to take my severance and start a wider job search.</p>

<p>I’m mostly looking in Europe since American democracy has been sabotaged by an authoritarian theocracy, but am also considering remote jobs in the States. Since the end of May, I’ve had… so many interviews. The hiring process has felt elongated: 4–5 interviews plus an assessment, with ~2 weeks between each step.</p>

<p>I guess I understand on one level—I can’t meet these hiring managers &amp; colleagues in person, so they probably want several opportunities to gauge my skillset &amp; temperament before investing in me (especially if they have to go through the extra effort to sponsor me for a visa). And everyone’s busy; exacerbated by the labor shortage (is that affecting all industries?). On another level, if everyone really is short-staffed, 10 weeks seems like a very long timeline to fill a vacancy.</p>

<p>Has hiring always been like this? I’ve mostly been applying to jobs in technology or fintech, so maybe it’s a self-selection bias.</p>

<h2 id="jay-hopler">Jay Hopler</h2>
<p>The poet <a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/jay-hopler">Jay Hopler</a> died in June after living with cancer for many years.</p>

<p>His first collection, <em>Green Squall</em>, won the 2005 <a href="http://youngerpoets.yupnet.org/">Yale Series of Younger Poets</a> (America’s oldest literary prize). I started writing poetry in a dedicated way in 2007 when I took <a href="https://www.kristinrobertson.net">Kristin Robertson’s</a> poetry workshop at UT. One day I turned in a draft, and when Kristin returned it, she had included a photocopy of Hopler’s title poem from that collection:</p>

<!-- Green Squall poem -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/greenSquall.png" alt="The title poem from Jay Hopler's 2005 collection 'Green Squall: for Kimberly Johnson / Lightning — / Now there's a sexy machete: a pounce of sky electric — / electricitied — inflamed. / What's the sugar, Hurricane? / The rain tins its romantic in the water pots. / The waterspouts are full-on / Rashmahanic. / What's the hurry, Sugarcane? / A pouncing sky enlightninged, / Edgy-sexed. . . . / This is the sugar. / This is the hurry." style="max-width: 65%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 65%"></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I became fixated on this poem. I was new to contemporary poetry at the time (because <a href="/howOurStudentsLearned#poetry-in-america-scratching-the-surface">our schools fail us</a> in this regard), and had no concept of this kind of playfulness: with grammar, with word-making, with imagery. I also loved seeing the poem stretch out &amp; take up space on the page (imagine what it would lose as a single stanza of left-aligned text). In the following months, I wrote several pastiches of the poems in <em>Green Squall</em>, including “Daydream”, which was recently published in <a href="https://www.poetrysalzburg.com/psr-no38.htm">Poetry Salzburg Review</a>, and is a pastiche of Hopler’s opening poem, “In the Garden”.</p>

<p>Ultimately, my poetic voice is very different from Hopler’s, but my first impulse was to imitate poets who, like him, are masters at the level of the phoneme. Because they make me want to slow down, stare into the middle distance, give my day to a collection of poems, despite the world burning &amp; drowning on either side of me. Because without artists like Jay Hopler &amp; the beauty they add to the world, what’s the fucking point?</p>

<p>McSweeney’s has been collecting <a href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/remembering-jay-hopler">remembrances of Jay</a>.</p>

<p>Rest well, dear great poet.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Republican Party has overthrown the United States government.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Municipal Works with Cars on Fire</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/municipalWorks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Municipal Works with Cars on Fire" /><published>2022-05-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-05-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/municipal-works</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/municipalWorks"><![CDATA[<p>I’m back from my trip to Albuquerque, and one of the coolest things about the city is all their public transportation is free. I was able to transverse the city to see places I could never have seen—and spend money at businesses I wouldn’t have otherwise visited—if my only options were walking or rideshare.<!-- here --></p>

<h2 id="a-rant-on-american-cities">A rant on American cities</h2>
<p>I’m gonna say something that may seem extreme (though I’ll bet not to most reading my blog)—public transportation should be a guaranteed service that every municipality provides. I’m not saying it’s a human right the way housing should be; I mean it’s self-evidently beneficial for every town/city/county/state/country to provide a way for its citizens to get from A to B. Even if you’re only looking at things through an economic lens.</p>

<p>Libertarians may believe in the myth of self-sufficiency, but the rest of us know that we depend on each other &amp; the collective resources of our communities to do <em>literally</em> anything. And I do mean the classic definition of “literally”. Usable roads don’t exist without taxation, city councils, regulation. Let alone things like first responders, teachers, &amp; drinkable water.</p>

<p>Speaking of community, public transportation also seems like a good baseline step for fostering one. American cities &amp; towns rarely have the infrastructure necessary to bring people together—whether that’s functional metros &amp; buses or something as basic as sidewalks. You know, places for human beings to safely exist. I think of churches as the way we’ve historically brought people together in the U.S.; but since younger generations like mine are less likely to attend church (for just so many reasons), there’s really no universal meeting ground. And even if we had some reason to congregate, how would we get there? I often don’t leave my house (even pre-COVID) because it’s not worth the hassle of driving and searching out &amp; paying to park.</p>

<p>Take my current city, Nashville:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The suburban layout separates areas of living, of industry, &amp; of commerce.<br />
There are few-to-zero bars, restaurants, or other types of recreation where people live; and almost no one lives near where they work.</li>
  <li>You must own a car; human beings have no safe place to exist outdoors.<br />
Many areas, even just a mile or two from downtown, don’t even have sidewalks. There’s a grocery store 0.2mi from my house, but to get there on foot, I’d have to walk in the narrow shoulder of a dangerous road where people often drive over 50mph. If I had to jump out of the way, it would be 8ft down into a drainage ditch.</li>
  <li>Public transportation, such as it exists, is useless.<br />
Nashville has no public transit except a bus system that employs a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spoke%E2%80%93hub_distribution_paradigm" target="_blank">spoke-hub distribution model</a>. Because all routes run inbound or outbound from the city center, it turns quick errands into half-day excursions.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="example-of-useless-public-transit">Example of useless public transit</h5>
<p>Let’s say you lived north of the city, and wanted to get to a grocery store that’s 2.5mi east. That’s about 45min of walking if you have no physical limitations. By car, less than 10min.</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m28!1m12!1m3!1d12875.828651656026!2d-86.75739715806424!3d36.21623613116685!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!4m13!3e0!4m5!1s0x88645d605bd6ee9f%3A0x37f9fe56fa368a0b!2s704%20Cottage%20Park%20Dr%2C%20Nashville%2C%20TN%2037207!3m2!1d36.2218139!2d-86.7634475!4m5!1s0x8864680526032667%3A0x365a10e5961af5a7!2sKroger%2C%203410%20Gallatin%20Pike%2C%20Nashville%2C%20TN%2037216!3m2!1d36.210136399999996!2d-86.73166479999999!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1651615366464!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="600" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
This is a random house I found in the area.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>But you don’t have a car, so you have to rely on the buses. Here’s Google’s recommended route:</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m28!1m12!1m3!1d51509.49279579343!2d-86.7860166163181!3d36.20684984910141!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!4m13!3e3!4m5!1s0x88645d605bd6ee9f%3A0x37f9fe56fa368a0b!2s704%20Cottage%20Park%20Dr%2C%20Nashville%2C%20TN%2037207!3m2!1d36.2218139!2d-86.7634475!4m5!1s0x8864680526032667%3A0x365a10e5961af5a7!2sKroger%2C%203410%20Gallatin%20Pike%2C%20Nashville%2C%20TN%2037216!3m2!1d36.210136399999996!2d-86.73166479999999!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1651616157887!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="600" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
Depending on the time of day, you're either looping north or south for a total trip of 45–60min.<br />The east–west connector on the northern route just began operating in April 2022.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The southern loop (the most-often recommended) requires two buses—the bus to the Central terminal is 5mi; the bus from Central to Kroger is another 4.5mi. With the transfer, it takes longer to get there with transit than to walk it. Hart Lane happens to have sidewalks along most of its stretch, so at least you don’t have to worry about drivers dicking around on their cell phones.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
The 23 bus that runs north-south on Dickerson Pike (one of Nashville's most crucial arteries) doesn't operate on weekends. So, you know, just go fuck yourself.
</div>

<p>In the interest of fairness—yes, there are closer grocery stores to that random house. But they’re a Piggly Wiggly &amp; an HG Hills, which are both only slight upgrades over a Family Dollar, and would both require walking down a busy 5-lane road that has no sidewalk.</p>

<p>So you really have to own a car in Nashville (or anywhere in the South).</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>Aside from some small clean-up efforts, the only real news to share is that I’ve been in touch with a couple professionals in the book publishing industry: <a href="https://www.pdx.edu/profile/kathi-inman-berens" target="_blank">Dr. Kathi Inman Berens</a> &amp; <a href="https://reedsy.com/emily-keough" target="_blank">Emily HagenBurger Keough</a>.</p>

<p>My focus right now is to finish a couple outstanding poems and finalize the order so the collection is ready for reviewers. I still have to decide how to distribute it to them. I currently have it in a public folder of my Dropbox, but this requires them to download the site to a local drive. It will open &amp; operate in a browser as normal, but it seems like more effort than necessary, and I suspect some won’t be willing to download the project onto their computers out of the (very reasonable) fear of a virus from a stranger.</p>

<p>A service like <a href="https://ngrok.com/" target="_blank">ngrok</a> will host the booksite, but I think I would need to keep a local server (my laptop) running 24/7. If I let my computer sleep, the booksite would be unavailable. I need to do some more research into temporary hosting.</p>

<h3 id="promotion--publicity">Promotion &amp; publicity</h3>
<p>My biggest takeaway from Emily’s advice is to focus on reviews, interviews, &amp; features in advance of publishing the book. So I’ve identified a decently sized list of bloggers &amp; journals who do book reviews, and some other outlets who may be interested in interviewing me about the book or its underlying technology. For the most part, soliciting reviews is a simple submission process. But since everything about my booksite is non-traditional, even this is complicated:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Some reviewers want a physical copy.<br />
I don’t and will likely never print this collection—not to mention that much of the project is eliminated outside a web-based medium.</li>
  <li>Others are fine with a PDF or ePub.<br />
That’s functionally equivalent to print, so again, a no-go.</li>
  <li>Some that are not on my list require payment.<br />
I think that’s fine; the review is, after all, work. But I’m not a business, and don’t have a budget for this. A big outlet like Kirkus charges $500! I also don’t want to spend money only for someone to publish a review that basically says “This project is dumb and the poems are trash”.</li>
</ul>

<p>By “features”, I’m referring to readings or events where my poetry is featured. I think I have another feature coming in 2023! Which would be my first since March 2020. But there’s the issue—reading series book out 12+ months in advance. And COVID still complicates whether it’s actually safe to hold the reading. I’m planning to chat with some people who run open mics that include a feature poet (usually a 15–20min set).</p>

<p>I’ve also been considering house readings, where a friend hosts a reading in their home. This requires a pretty big commitment from the friend, though; not to mention the logistics of planning an event (food, drinks, chairs, merch, PA system, etc.). I’ve never participated in or been to one, but it seems like it could be intimate &amp; fun.</p>

<h2 id="submissions">Submissions</h2>
<p>My last forthcoming publication (<a href="https://www.poetrysalzburg.com/psr-no38.htm" target="_blank">Poetry Salzburg Review</a>) is now out in print.</p>

<p>No regular journal submissions recently; though, I have applied &amp; submitted for other opportunities:</p>

<h3 id="fellowships">Fellowships</h3>
<p>Got my <strong>National Endowment for the Arts (NEA)</strong> grant application in. Having completed it in 2020, it wasn’t as awful this time around. But wow, what a malicious application process. If they had intended to make it as frustrating &amp; confusing as possible, I don’t see how they could have done a better job.</p>

<p>I’m grateful that American writers have the opportunity to receive these funds, which are set aside simply to perpetuate art—but there’s really no excuse for such a poor user experience. I’m not going into detail here because, among writers, the NEA application is famously awful, and much is written about it every spring.</p>

<p>I also stumbled across a <a href="https://www.justbuffalo.org/fellowships/poetry-fellowship" target="_blank">poetry-specific fellowship</a> in my hometown with the <strong>Just Buffalo Literary Center</strong>. It includes a stipend, lodging for a month, &amp; a reading at their Silo Reading Series. I grew up close to those grain silos, in the neighborhood of Riverside. They’re giants in my memory, prominently featured in many of the first poems I ever wrote. To read there would be magical for me.</p>

<h3 id="chapbooks">Chapbooks</h3>
<p>At the beginning of the year, I noticed a few relatively inexpensive chapbook submission opportunities, and finally put one together on the theme of masculinity. I submitted to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Button</li>
  <li>Rattle (already rejected <em class="fas fa-grin-tears"></em>)</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.sundresspublications.com/safta" target="_blank">SAFTA</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Even though I’m releasing the booksite as a full manuscript later this year, I think having my name to something with an established publisher will augment my promotion efforts for <em>The Great Permission</em>.</p>

<h2 id="personal-stuff">Personal stuff</h2>
<h3 id="tattoos">Tattoos</h3>
<p>My favorite poet remains Jack Gilbert; his collection, <em>The Great Fires</em> has easily been the most impactful book on my writing. I want a half-sleeve that represents the last line of his poem “The Forgotten Dialect of the Heart”:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>What we feel most has<br />
no name but amber, archers, cinnamon, horses and birds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I decided on a literal interpretation that simply includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>a block of amber</li>
  <li>an archer with a bow</li>
  <li>a quill of cinnamon</li>
  <li>a horse</li>
  <li>a blue swallow</li>
</ul>

<p>The <a href="https://www.instagram.com/tattooartist_soyeon/" target="_blank">tattoo artist</a> I <em>really</em> want to work with finally opened her books for the first time in a full calendar year. I didn’t get a response last year, so I’m hopeful I’ll get to schedule with her this time around. If not, I found a couple other artists whose style I like.</p>

<h3 id="buddy">Buddy</h3>
<p>My parents made the decision to put down their dog in March. He was about 17, and his body had been falling apart. I did get to say goodbye to him when I helped my parents move back to Buffalo in mid-February. It was painful to watch him struggle to walk; his hips seemed to be detached from their sockets. I had to carry him down the few steps to the backyard so he could pee &amp; poop. He had lost his senses of smell &amp; hearing long ago, and I think he was mostly blind by the end. His body was covered with (benign) tumors, and his teeth were rotting (the dentist had said years ago that he was already too old to be put under).</p>

<p>Still, I’m grateful I was able to see him one last time. It’s rare to have &amp; recognize that opportunity. Here’s the <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Ca0e4ycAdp8/?utm_source=ig_web_copy_link" target="_blank">IG post</a> I wrote about his death.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m back from my trip to Albuquerque, and one of the coolest things about the city is all their public transportation is free. I was able to transverse the city to see places I could never have seen—and spend money at businesses I wouldn’t have otherwise visited—if my only options were walking or rideshare.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Computer on Which I Troubleshoot</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/computerTroubleshoot" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Computer on Which I Troubleshoot" /><published>2022-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/the-computer-on-which</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/computerTroubleshoot"><![CDATA[<p>We’re still in the habit of asking people “How was your week/weekend?” or “What have you been up to?” But since every day is the same and time has no meaning anymore, I have no answers. <!-- here -->Especially since most of the people asking those questions are colleagues or casual acquaintances. I’m not telling them about how I watched Rick &amp; Morty s5 in one sitting, or <em>all my computer problems</em>.</p>

<h2 id="publications">Publications</h2>
<p>I’ve had several poems published recently! Sort of a coincidence that the publishing schedules all lined up in this three month period, because they were all accepted at different times—one a full year ago:</p>
<ul>
  <li>5 poems in the <a href="https://www.ws.edu/_media/pdf/special-events/mildred/review/2021-review.pdf">Mildred Haun Review</a></li>
  <li>1 poem in <a href="https://thewildword.com/poetry-andrew-p-dillon">The Wild Word</a></li>
  <li>1 poem in <a href="https://www.stirringlit.com/vol-24-ed-1-p-dead-letters-by-andrew-p-dillon">Stirring</a></li>
  <li>1 poem in <a href="https://www.westreview.org/what-he-didnt.html">The West Review</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve also got 2 poems forthcoming in print in <a href="http://www.poetrysalzburg.com/psr-main.htm">Poetry Salzburg Review</a>, which will now be a Spring 2022 pub, rather than the Winter 2021 release that was planned. The editor recently posted that the master copy is with the printer, so… however long it takes to print then ship. (From Austria.)</p>

<h3 id="submissions">Submissions</h3>
<p>I was on a streak, submitting poems most days November–January. There are probably 30 submissions still awaiting reply (plus a few chapbook contests). 30 submissions represents about 150 poems, and with my lifetime acceptance rate around 3% of the total poems I submit, I can probably expect another 4–5 poems published.</p>

<p>No submissions since the end of January, though. After doing a clean migration to a new computer whose OS no longer supports PHP, I’m still redesigning my submission architecture. Big surprise, it wasn’t as easy as <a href="/dreamCommonSub#page-level-variables">I made it out to be</a>. More on this <a href="#migrating">below</a>.</p>

<h2 id="this-site">This site</h2>
<p>A few small changes here. I removed the <em>About</em> page, and added its content to the homepage. It didn’t seem necessary to have a separate page for my short bio and contact info while I had a homepage with no content except a headshot. Considering getting rid of the Contact info panel, since all that info is in the footer of every page.</p>

<p>I hate my homepage, actually. It’s boring, and I don’t think the elements really work together; it looks, I dunno, blocky. I need to spend some time revising. I also need a new headshot in advance of releasing the book, and since the current one is 8 years old.</p>

<p>On the <a href="/links">Links page</a>, all my poetry publications are now visible. I can’t remember now why I decided to highlight only some of them; it’s not like I have an unwieldy number of credits. Several of the journals &amp; their websites are now defunct, and others were published in print, so many of my published poems aren’t available at all. Which brings me to my final update on this site, the <em>Read</em> page.</p>

<h3 id="read-page">Read page</h3>
<p>It’s not quite ready yet. Because I <a href="#symlinks">solved my single-sourcing issue</a>, I now have all my poems available in the repo for this website. The plan is to use the <em>Read</em> page to display all my published poems that are:</p>
<ul>
  <li>unavailable because the journal folded.</li>
  <li>older than one year (preferring to direct traffic to the journal until then).</li>
</ul>

<p>But I can’t figure out the code to disallow pubs less than a year old <em class="far fa-meh-rolling-eyes"></em></p>

<p>Dates are tricky in Liquid. I can’t just say something like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if date ≤ ('now' - 365)</code>. In Liquid, you can only use operators (==, !=, &lt;, &lt;=, &gt;, &gt;=, or, and) within control flow tags (if, unless, case/when). But you can’t use filters in any of those tags to limit output; and most of the useful filters (like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">where</code>) only act on arrays. Basically, it takes too much effort to compare dates. And Liquid (sometimes?) treats them as strings instead of numbers or, ya know, dates.</p>

<p>One solution <em>should be</em> to convert all dates to Unix time (the number of seconds since   <time datetime="1970-01-01T00:00:00">midnight 01 Jan 1970</time>
), subtract the published date from today’s date, and ensure that number is greater than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">31,556,926</code> (the number of seconds in a non-leap year). It’s basically how I wrote the <em>Links</em> page to say “forthcoming” if the issue hasn’t been released yet. But it’s not working, and I haven’t figured it out yet.</p>

<p>Of course, that solution will only reflect dates at the second I build my site, before pushing to the GitHub repo. Javascript should be able to keep all my date-dependent code current, but I’m only just now learning that language.</p>

<h2 id="migrating">Migrating</h2>
<p>My old computer was experiencing increasingly regular kernel panics (like a crash, but more severe because it’s related to the core program within your operating system), so I bought a new computer before the old one could brick on me. Because of the kernel panics, I decided to do a clean migration to avoid accidentally bringing over whatever corrupt file was fucking up the old computer. I thought it would be a good learning experience, but it was just a massive pain in the ass.</p>

<h3 id="users">Users</h3>
<p>I decided to implement the common security practice of setting up a standard user for day-to-day use, separate from the admin user you create when you first power on a new computer. The rationale being that Admin has access to everything on the computer, so if you get phished or download the wrong file, the scammer has full access; Standard users have a more limited scope, so a scammer can do less damage.</p>

<p>All that sounds great, but for people like me who use a lot of open-source tools, it requires updating PATH variables for every tool or language. This is usually poorly documented, if at all. It’s also scary because you’re running command line commands to edit configuration files. Entering the wrong PATH probably won’t screw anything up that you can’t easily fix, but there are other elements in those files that <em>will</em> fuck up your computer should you mistype.</p>

<h3 id="jekyll">Jekyll</h3>
<p>I won’t get into all the details, but getting my Jekyll projects up &amp; running was… infuriating. In theory, you just clone the repo from GitHub, but the gem theme directory structure complicates it.</p>

<p>Jekyll allows you to choose a theme (or skin) for your site, and while the project directory can be anywhere (like your desktop), the files for the theme are buried in the directory for whatever tool you use to manage Ruby (RVM, in my case).</p>

<p>I ended up moving all the necessary theme files into the project folders, then transferring the files over Airdrop. I have two projects that use the same theme (this site &amp; my submissions project); with the gem theme directory structure, all those files are shared. Which I think is very stupid. Unless you want both projects to have the exact same layouts, headers, footers, &amp; stylesheets, it only makes things harder as a user.</p>

<h3 id="dotfiles">Dotfiles</h3>
<p>Finally (and this was my dumb fault), I used a tool called Mackup to transfer my <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hidden_file_and_hidden_directory">dotfiles</a>. That temporarily fucked everything up because I continued to use the old computer. I didn’t realize (but should have) that Mackup was <em>syncing</em> those files (it uses your Dropbox or similar account). So I ended up with important config files being shared with both computers (oops) as aliases (shit). Fortunately, once I uninstalled Mackup, everything went back to normal.</p>

<h3 id="symlinks">Symlinks</h3>
<p>The big thing that migrating forced me to deal with was my bad practice of <a href="dreamCommonSub#true-single-sourcing-with-submodules">maintaining multiple copies</a> of my poems. To recap, I have three projects that might need to use my poems:</p>
<ul>
  <li>this site</li>
  <li>the <a href="/tgp">booksite</a></li>
  <li>a setup for creating submissions</li>
</ul>

<p>Two of those three had their own copies of each poem (I’ve been holding off adding poems to this site so as not to create another copy):</p>
<ul>
  <li>The booksite is another Jekyll project, so those poems needed YAML frontmatter.</li>
  <li>The <a href="/dreamCommonSub#submission-architecture">submissions setup on the old computer</a> used the built-in Apache server, with poems written in HTML and compiled with a PHP template.</li>
</ul>

<p>Given two different formats, they couldn’t have been shared. In some macOS update after my old computer wasn’t able to upgrade anymore, Mac deprecated support for PHP. Rather than recreate that setup, I figured I could use Jekyll to create submission documents.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
I decided not to change anything with the poems in the booksite. They have custom frontmatter elements for navigation &amp; notes that would be meaningless in another project. Plus, I want the booksite to remain static after I release it; I don't want any future edits to those poems to get pushed to the booksite.
</div>

<p>To have a single source of poems, I tested Git submodules. But because Git is trash, it wasn’t a solution. First of all, the files in the submodule weren’t available in the superprojects I added them to—Jekyll basically acted like they weren’t there. And even if it had worked, that setup would have required me to run <em>all</em> of the following commands <em>each time</em> I updated any poem:</p>

<p><em>in the submodule (poems) repo</em></p>
<ol>
  <li>git add</li>
  <li>git commit</li>
  <li>git push</li>
</ol>

<p><em>in <strong>each</strong> superproject (repos using the poems)</em></p>
<ol>
  <li>git submodule update –remote</li>
  <li>git add</li>
  <li>git commit</li>
  <li>git push</li>
</ol>

<p>Finally, I remembered that another Jekyll Talk user <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/t/is-it-possible-to-single-source-files-across-jekyll-projects/5565">suggested</a> I look into symlinks. And they work seamlessly! I just ran the following Zsh command (in Terminal) for each project where I want the poems to be available:</p>
<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">ln</span> <span class="nt">-s</span> path/to/poems path/to/project
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>And that’s it! <em class="fas fa-glass-cheers"></em> All my poems are now persistently available in this project &amp; the submissions project.</p>

<p>As far as I can tell, the only real downside here is that <em>every</em> poem gets pulled into the build, even the ones that aren’t being used anywhere. For this site, that’s kind of a pain in the ass, since the GitHub repo has to be public in order for GH Pages to read &amp; serve it, and a lot of journals have strict interpretations of what constitutes “previous publication”. So I have to manually remove those files.</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>No real progress here because of all the time I spent dealing with the new computer. I have some time away from work coming up that I plan to devote to the book; specifically communicating with a friend who works in book promotion.</p>

<h2 id="bjj">BJJ</h2>
<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
  <p>I'm a beginner to BJJ, which is a very complicated discipline, full of nuance.</p>
  <p>Please contextualize my observations &amp; opinions as those of someone who understands very little.</p>
</div>

<p>This week, I used a Kimura to tap someone in a roll while I had him in full guard.</p>

<p>That was probably a weird sentence for anyone reading this blog, so let me break it down:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armlock#Kimura_(Gyaku_ude-garami)">Kimura</a></strong> is an arm &amp; shoulder lock, named after Masahiko Kimura (regarded as the judo GOAT).</li>
  <li><strong>tap</strong> means I submitted my opponent—I made him tap.</li>
  <li><strong>roll</strong> is a spar, or a practice fight.</li>
  <li><strong>guard</strong> is a position. When I’m on the ground and my opponent is above me, I’m “in guard”.<br /><strong>Full guard</strong> means I’m on my back with my legs around my opponent’s torso and ankles locked; here, my opponent is “in my guard”. (Counterintuitively, if I have an opponent in full guard, <em>I</em> am in the advantageous position.)</li>
</ul>

<p>I’d never managed it from that position, so I felt like a total boss. The Kimura (or the similar Americana) is my favorite submission; I go for it a lot, mostly failing. I’m trying to master them because (from my inexpert perspective) one of them is available from pretty much every position.</p>

<p>Mostly, I got my ass kicked again this week. I’m very sore because one roll was with a black belt, and he basically decided what my body would be doing for those three minutes.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="bjj" /><category term="publications" /><category term="submissions" /><category term="techJourney" /><category term="troubleshooting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re still in the habit of asking people “How was your week/weekend?” or “What have you been up to?” But since every day is the same and time has no meaning anymore, I have no answers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Which Language Do I Keep Blogging</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/inWhichLanguage" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Which Language Do I Keep Blogging" /><published>2021-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/in-which-language</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/inWhichLanguage"><![CDATA[<p>I cannot conceive of more concrete evidence of America as a failed state than our regular need for heroic teenage bullet sponges. <!-- here -->Tate Myer is the latest victim of America’s childish obsession with guns. Usually, when a news item erodes what little faith I have rebuilt in people, I can console myself with the fact that it’s reporting by exception. But in America, a day without gun violence <em>is</em> the exception.</p>

<h2 id="publications">Publications</h2>
<p>My poem <a href="https://thewestreview.weebly.com/what-he-didnt.html"><cite class="poem">What He Didn’t Know Before</cite></a> was published in the new issue of <a href="https://www.westreview.org/current-issue.html"><cite class="journal">The West Review</cite></a>. It’s such a strong issue. And I was so happy to have my poem alongside <a href="https://www.westreview.org/to-be-honest.html"><cite class="poem">To Be Honest, Not At All Like Fine Wine</cite></a> by <a href="http://donnavorreyer.com">Donna Vorreyer</a>, whose newest collection, <cite class="book">To Everything There Is</cite>, I’ve read through a few times this year.</p>

<p>I’m expecting two more journals to publish accepted poems before the end of the year: <a href="https://www.ws.edu/special-events/mildred-haun/review/"><cite class="journal">The Mildred Haun Review</cite></a> &amp; <a href="http://www.poetrysalzburg.com/psr-main.htm"><cite class="journal">Poetry Salzburg Review</cite></a>. Both are supposed to be 2021 issues, anyway. I also have some poems being held by a journal that’s published me before.</p>

<p>Submitting can be frustrating, tiring work, but when I’m consistent, I usually see results. My lifetime acceptance rate is somewhere around 3% of the total poems I have submitted. Though I think it’s a bit higher in recent years as I’ve developed as a writer and my name is more recognizable within certain literary enclaves.</p>

<h2 id="favicon">Favicon</h2>
<p>See that little icon in your browser tab? That’s new! I finally got sick of Terminal telling me I was missing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">favicon.ico</code>, and used <a href="https://favicon.io">favicon.io</a> to make one. It’s just my initials, but now this feels like a Real Website. I did the same for the booksite. I also put a larger <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">png</code> of the favicon in the footer, and cleaned up some of the text there.</p>

<!-- Favicon 192x192 -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/android-chrome-192x192.png" alt="An enlarged copy of this website's favicon: a circle containing the author's initials (APD) on a light blue background (hex code #31b0d5)" style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
A 192px copy for some reason
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>No other updates to this site. I think it’s serving its purpose as a digital landing page for my writing; though I suspect more people actually view <a href="https://www.instagram.com/andrewdillonpoetry">my Instagram</a>, which is <em>not saying much</em>.</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>Lots of small, unremarkable progress on the backend. Mostly applying &amp; paring down tooltips, keywords, &amp; notes. One update is that I changed the subtitle from the simple &amp; obvious “Poems” to “A reliquary”. Some background here:</p>

<p>I was talking to a potential editor (more below), and after I explained that <a href="https://www.commonpodcast.com/home/2019/11/18/episode-77-tina-chang">Rachel Zucker’s conversation with Tina Chang</a> was a major turning point for my conception of the book, they told me about Nikki Finney’s <cite class="book">Love Child’s Hotbed of Occasional Poetry: Poems and Artifacts</cite>. It clicked for me that my booksite—already pushing against what a collection of poetry looks like &amp; how it exists in the world, and with the pictures, recipes, &amp; notes—<em>is</em> more than a collection of poems. Its scope is larger.</p>

<!-- TGP Reliquary screenshot -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/tgpReliquary.png" alt="A screenshot of the homepage of the author's forthcoming booksite, with the subtitle 'A reliquary' &amp; the author's name magnified." style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
A small, meaningful update
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So the booksite is now “A reliquary”—a collection of relics. There’s some religious connotation there, which I’m happy to lean into, since the poems, images, &amp; recipes (and people contained within all of them) are the things I have faith in. I don’t believe any higher power has ever existed—and if it does, it’s clear to me that it is unworthy of praise. These relics are what most influence my behavior, what shape my worldview, and provide a framework for my moral &amp; ethical bounds. They’re also expressions of how I, my worldview, &amp; ethics developed. It felt correct the moment the word popped into my head as a possibility.</p>

<h3 id="an-editor">An editor</h3>
<p>Maybe! I had a video call with someone early this month to discuss my project &amp; their availability. The timing may not work out on their end, but I’m hopeful that this person, who’s part of my local poetry community, will decide to take this on. And that I can afford their quote.</p>

<p>I want an editor because I don’t know how objective I can be about these poems anymore. Or, while I can probably be honest about individual poems, I don’t know if I can still clearly see the connections between them, or evaluate the collection as a whole.</p>

<h4 id="readers">Readers</h4>
<p>How… how does this work? No one’s ever asked me to read their manuscript before they submitted it for publication. My sense is that poets just help each other out by offering limited developmental feedback, but how do you initiate this conversation? Should I offer to pay? How many readers should I reach out to? I think in a future post, I’ll elaborate on the deep discomfort of asking people to do favors for me.</p>

<h3 id="cover-art">Cover art</h3>
<p>I’ll have some original cover art for the release. Currently, the “cover art” on my homepage is the following image:
<!-- Blood Clot Pre --></p>
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/bloodClotPre.png" alt="An anterior view ultrasound of the author's right shoulder before a venogram, showing blood obstructed in the subclavian vein. The dark areas indicate blood vessels where blood is stagnant." style="max-width: 60%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 60%">
A scan of a still captured by my ultrasound tech before the venogram to remove my blood clot
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It works on a certain level, given the ethos of my project. But it’s also a low-quality, somewhat inscrutable image. And the collection really isn’t about recovery. Some poems are, but not many.</p>

<p>So the new cover art will be an NFT minted specifically for my booksite, which is part of a collection one of my friends is developing, and which should be available before my booksite is ready. I won’t reveal the image before the release, but I will link to the project from here when it’s live. I want to tell you all about it because it’s very exciting to me, and I’m so proud of my friend for developing it! But it’s still under development, so I don’t want to misrepresent anything in case they revise.</p>

<h3 id="marketing--publicity">Marketing &amp; publicity</h3>
<p>I haven’t been very active with my publicity plan &amp; timeline, except to stay present in my literary communities and continue submitting individual poems. To that end, I’ve been attending all my regular open mics.</p>

<h4 id="open-mics">Open mics</h4>
<p>I don’t really think of open mics as publicity so much as literary citizenship, but it is a way to keep my name on people’s lips, so feels like it placing under the “publicity” header isn’t wrong.</p>

<p>I attended <a href="https://poetryinthebrew.wordpress.com">Poetry in the Brew’s</a> December event, featuring Carolyn Connolly. Decembers are always thin, but we ended up with a respectable crowd of ~25.
<!-- PitB screenshot --></p>
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/mePitB_Dec2021.png" alt="" style="max-width: 50%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 50%">
Live at Portland Brew East, 11 Dec 2021<br />Credit: Christine Hall
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On the 14<sup>th</sup>, I attended <a href="https://www.facebook.com/poetryblackdogbookco">Black Dog’s</a> December virtual open mic, featuring one of our hosts, <a href="http://www.sandycoomer.com">Sandy Coomer</a>, reading from her new collection, <cite class="book">The Broken Places</cite>. They announced that starting in January 2022, they’ll be holding the event live from the Lipscomb University campus, simulcast on Zoom. This seems perfect, since the series regularly includes readers from England &amp; India.</p>

<p>I’ve also started sporadically attending <a href="https://www.rattle.com/rattlecast">Rattlecast</a>. They’re live weekly on Sundays, usually at 8pm Eastern. I hate Sundays (a relic of being raised Catholic), and rarely want to do anything those days. But it’s an international audience, attracting excellent feature writers, hosted by the editor of the literary journal with one of the largest readerships.</p>

<p>I think of open mics as a great space to unveil new material. As in: newly completed drafts. I find it helpful to stand in front of a live audience and read baby poems to get a sense of how the audience receives them and how they inhabit the space. (I haven’t found this to be true of virtual events, unfortunately.) Of course, in that case, a lot depends on the audience &amp; space. Some audiences (white ones) don’t tend to give much feedback; some spaces have bad (fluorescent) lighting, lots of echo, or are physically uncomfortable (stools). Still, I’d always rather be in a room with the poet/audience.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
<strong>Open mic etiquette</strong>   <p>If you're one of those people who writes poems <em>during</em> the open mic to read during your 5, please stop doing that.</p>
  <p>First of all, it's so fucking rude to not give each reader the attention they're going to give you.</p>
  <p>Second, those poems are always terrible. Work on it in your private time; bring it back next month.</p>
</div>

<h3 id="navtabs">Navtabs</h3>
<p>The layout file for poems includes code to build navigation tabs that hold the notes, any publication history, &amp; lists of related poems within the booksite (based on keywords I apply to them). Generating the lists of related poems hasn’t caused me any trouble, but I had an issue in which the publication note either wasn’t rendering, or was being duplicated. I did identify the issue and resolve it—by taking the lazy route.</p>

<h4 id="about-this-poem">About this poem</h4>
<p>Here’s the <em>About this poem</em> tab working correctly:</p>

<!-- Dust: Notes screenshot -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/dustAbout.png" alt="" style="max-width: 60%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 60%"></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I originally tried to write some logic that would check the frontmatter for a value in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code> key and, depending on whether there were multiple notes (as an array) or a single string, format the tab as a list or a paragraph.</p>

<p>Additionally, if the poem had been published (indicated by the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">publishedFlag</code> frontmatter key), it would add a line containing the value in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">journal</code> key and format the whole tab as:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>a list</strong> if there were any notes.</li>
  <li><strong>a paragraph</strong> if there were no notes.</li>
</ul>

<p>At first, I added the logic that grabbed the publication note <em>inside</em> a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">for</code> loop, so <em>for</em> every array item in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code>, it would generate the pubnote. That was easy to identify &amp; fix. I’m not entirely sure what caused my other issue—the pubnote simply not rendering. It seems to have been related to my use of YAML chomp modifiers. If I used one to prepend the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code> value (if it was not an array), the pubnote didn’t render.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
<strong>String theory</strong>   <p>To glimpse the depth of my confusion on chomp modifiers, see this <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/21699210">Stack Overflow answer</a> on how to apply the <strong>63 different</strong> modifier permutations.</p>
</div>

<p>Eventually, I noticed that when I formatted <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notes</code> as an array (even if there was only a single note), everything rendered correctly with no errors. Of course, that meant that the <em>About</em> tab would always be formatted as a list if it included a note (though not if there were a pubnote &amp; no notes, as above). Which… fine. I dislike the inconsistency, but I’m tired of fucking with it. Here’s that code:</p>

<div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">capture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">aboutTitle</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">layout</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"poem"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="ow">or</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"dedication.html"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      About this poem
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">elsif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="ow">contains</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"recipe"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      About this recipe
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">elsif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="ow">contains</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"workout"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      About this workout
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endcapture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">notes</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">notes</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">first</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- if the NOTES frontmatter contains a list --&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page.notes</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- create a list item for each NOTE --&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/li&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">publishedFlag</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- include the publication note in the list --&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;This poem was first published in &lt;cite class="journal"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">journal-</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">elsif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">notes</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- if the NOTES frontmatter does not contain a list but does contain a string --&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">publishedFlag</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- create a list if there's a publication note --&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">notes</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This poem was first published in &lt;cite class="journal"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">journal-</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- the NOTES frontmatter is empty --&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">unless</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">publishedFlag</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span> &lt;!-- there's no publication note --&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No notes about this poem!&lt;/p&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endunless</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">publishedFlag</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    &lt;p&gt;This poem was first published in &lt;cite class="journal"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">journal-</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>So my comments in there are not totally accurate, but all the notes &amp; publication credits are rendering legibly on each poem, so I’m content.</p>

<h4 id="related-poems">Related poems</h4>
<p>The lists here are conceptually simpler. Here’s an example from the same poem as above (<cite class="poem">Dust</cite>):
<!-- Dust: Related screenshot --></p>
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/dustRelated.png" alt="" style="max-width: 60%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 60%"></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As you can see, those are all poems that start with ‘A’; the list is much longer. So I have some work to do in order to restrict the keywords. I don’t want it generating an unwieldy 5 lists of 10 poems, as it is on some poems.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, because the book is a static site, it can’t generate a random list each time the page is loaded. I could generate a random list with Liquid, but it would only be randomized when the site is built, which I’ll only be doing once per version. Possibly Javascript could handle this, but:</p>
<ul>
  <li>I don’t know Javascript.</li>
  <li>I’d probably have to reformat the content in my repo to make it available to Js on the client side.</li>
</ul>

<p>Anyway! Here’s how the Related lists are built:</p>

<div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisSeries</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">series</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisKey</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">keywords</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">items</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">sort</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"title"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisSeries</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="ow">or</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">data</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poemlists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="err">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">where</span><span class="err">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"allowedKeywords"</span><span class="err">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"thisKey"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisSeries</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;h5&gt;More poems in the &lt;b&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">data</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poemlists</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">series</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">thisSeries</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/b&gt; series:&lt;/h5&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">items</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">series</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisSeries</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
          <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">continue</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;/ul&gt;
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">allowed</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">data</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poemlists</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">allowedKeywords</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">keywords</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page.keywords</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">allowed</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="ow">contains</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"ars poetica"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      &lt;h5&gt;More ars poetica:&lt;/h5&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">elsif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"singing"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      &lt;h5&gt;More poems to sing:&lt;/h5&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">elsif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"body"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      &lt;h5&gt;More poems about the body:&lt;/h5&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">elsif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"funny"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      &lt;h5&gt;More poems with a laugh:&lt;/h5&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      &lt;h5&gt;More poems about <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">capitalize</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>:&lt;/h5&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    &lt;ul&gt;
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">items</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">keywords</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="ow">contains</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">key</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
          <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
            <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">continue</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
          <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">permalink</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    &lt;p&gt;No related poems!&lt;/p&gt;
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">allowedKeywords</code> asset is meant to keep things under control, but that list ballooned too. And I’m just noticing that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">{% else %}</code> clause (for poems with no matching allowedKeywords) at the end is not rendering. So there is something wrong there <em class="far fa-meh-blank"></em></p>

<h2 id="personal-matters">Personal matters</h2>
<p>In <a href="/windblows">an earlier post</a>, I mentioned applying for a Fulbright. Adorable. I suppose I’d get nowhere if I didn’t have some kind of ambition. I did not have time to organize that mess of an application, so I won’t be thinking about it until maybe next year, after the <a href="https://www.arts.gov/grants/creative-writing-fellowships">NEA</a> application, which is open for poetry in 2022.</p>

<p>And the Buffalo Bills. Ole triflin-ass team of my youth. At least you can say they’re reliable.</p>

<h3 id="rto">RTO</h3>
<p>Last week, I returned to my office for the first time in 20 months! Just for a day, but it was precisely the change of pace I hoped it would be. A few of my coworkers also came in, and it was so nice to see &amp; interact with other humans. I don’t like having my professional life invade my home, and I focus better (on any project) when I’m not where I live. Most of my colleagues &amp; I are now “flex” employees, who can effectively decide where we’ll work from on any given day; I’ll likely spend 1 day in the office per week.</p>

<h3 id="new-unpredictable-normal">New (unpredictable) normal</h3>
<p>I lived through another tornado—the 11 December tornados that hit six states. Nashville can technically experience a tornado anytime, but December is the second least likely month for those conditions to coalesce. We’re not supposed to have to worry about this now. I’m holding together gratitude for experiencing only minor cosmetic damage to my roof with fury that we keep choosing to allow these conditions.</p>

<p>I have a lot to say (big surprise) on the climate emergency, but I’ll end by saying I’m livid to acknowledge that these events will only increase in frequency &amp; unpredictability, and that I’m helpless to do much other than relocate to an area that seems like maybe it will be safer.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="marketing" /><category term="personal" /><category term="publications" /><category term="techJourney" /><category term="tgp" /><category term="troubleshooting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I cannot conceive of more concrete evidence of America as a failed state than our regular need for heroic teenage bullet sponges.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Light Around the Blog</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/lightAroundBlog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Light Around the Blog" /><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/the-light-around-the-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/lightAroundBlog"><![CDATA[<p>I don’t know about the rest of you, but I’m tired of waiting for the mutant limbs I was guaranteed after getting my COVID vaccines.<!-- here --> The CDC has expanded eligibility for COVID vaccine boosters to all adults, and at this point I feel like I’m owed at least an extra arm, if not super powers.</p>

<h2 id="publications">Publications</h2>
<p>I got a new acceptance this week! I’m very excited about my poem that’s forthcoming in <em><a href="http://www.westreview.org">The West Review</a></em>, <cite class="poem">What He Didn’t Know Before</cite>. It’s <em>in conversation</em> with Ada Limón’s <a href="https://www.washingtonsquarereview.com/ada-limn"><cite class="poem">What I Didn’t Know Before</cite></a>.</p>

<p>It’s one of those poems that, when I finished it, I thought “This is a great poem.” I believe in all the poems I submit (or I wouldn’t consider them ready to submit), but occasionally I write one that I feel in my bones can stand alongside the best poetry being written right now.</p>

<p>When I say “feel in my bones”, I do mean that somewhat literally. You know how when you experience a great piece of art, you have a physical reaction to it—maybe you cry or feel a tingle in your chest or your focus is suddenly razor-sharp? I know I’ve written something special when, after I’ve gone through the drafting &amp; revision processes, and let it sit, and then return to it, I still feel a blossoming as though the poem were just coming in to me.</p>

<p>I had a sincere exchange with <em>The West Review</em>’s Editor-in-Chief, <a href="https://www.despyboutris.com">Despy Boutris</a>, about one word in the poem, where we expressed our positions and came to what I think is a good compromise. I love working with editors. I admit that my knee-jerk reaction is always incredulity whenever someone wants to change my work, but I would also say that any change I’ve made in concert with an editor has unequivocally improved the poem. I’m grateful for the time &amp; energy that other people spend on my work.</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>Things are moving along! I decided that, no matter what, I’m releasing the book in 2022. I already own the domain, and it’s, strictly speaking, a functional website right now, so I’m not going to allow myself to delay it beyond next year. Very excited to have made that decision, and a huge relief.</p>

<h3 id="looavulluhvulloueyville">Looavul/Luhvul/Loueyville</h3>
<p>Definitely <em>not</em> /loo-is-ville/. (I could really use an IPA character set on this blog.)</p>

<p>I spent last week in Louisville, Kentucky, working on the booksite. I’ve visited a handful of times, and it’s maybe my favorite Southern city. I got more done that I expected, but less than I hoped. The marketing plan took more time than I expected. Who could have guessed that the work of an entire industry would be challenging for a complete novice? <em class="far fa-surprise"></em></p>

<p>Like any writing retreat, the great benefit of taking this trip was uninterrupted time to focus on my project. And as usual, it was glorious. I completed some long-incomplete drafts, submitted every day (my acceptance above came from a submission during this week!), walked several miles per day through beautiful Old Louisville, drank some very good coffee &amp; beer, and came up with some crazy, interesting ideas for how to publicize the book. Not having to context-shift every 20 minutes like I do in my normal life, I was making connections constantly (what is creativity other than these novel connections?)</p>

<!-- Louisville leaves screenshot -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/oldLouisvilleLeaves.png" alt="A street in Old Louisville, showing the sidewalk covered with leaves of many colors" style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
The entire city was absolutely <em>littered</em> with leaves
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The retreat also highlighted some kind of <a href="https://www.dictionaryofobscuresorrows.com">obscure sorrow</a>—acknowledging all the work I can’t &amp; may never complete because I simply don’t have time while living in a coercive, exploitative economic system that forces me to sell my labor for capital to produce objectively meaningless work, and to make that the first &amp; driving priority in my life. I know that sounds a bit sardonic &amp; screedy, but I think that sentiment really is universal enough that we should have a phrase or word for it. I’m not a linguist, someone help.</p>

<h3 id="spreading-the-word">Spreading the word</h3>
<p>I’ve been creating a plan to publicize the book, and having this inviolable time to concentrate on my creative life resulted in some of the crazy ideas I mentioned above. I won’t undertake all of these, but they’re kicking around now:</p>

<h4 id="beer">Beer</h4>
<p>My best friend, Brandon Cox, is the General Manager at <a href="https://www.southerngristbrewing.com">Southern Grist Brewing</a>, and also a talented homebrewer. I would love to collaborate on a recipe and can/bottle a limited run. I’ve even thought of a few poem-themed beer names.</p>

<h4 id="podcast">Podcast</h4>
<p>This really has less to do with publicity for the book than scratching an itch. One of the most interesting things in the world to me is simply someone talking about something they’re passionate about. Obviously, there are plenty of those podcasts out there, so mine would add a poetic element, with the idea of responding to Dana Gioia’s <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/unbound/poetry/gioia/gioia.htm">now-pretty-old recommendations</a> for reinvigorating poetry in the American consciousness.</p>

<p>I have, I think, a solid format in mind. And ideas for several guests. The issue, as always, will be my capacity and that of the guests.</p>

<h4 id="book-trailer">Book trailer</h4>
<p><a href="https://www.eugenialeigh.com">Eugenia Leigh</a> created a trailer for her book <cite class="book">Blood, Sparrows and Sparrows</cite>. I have a lot of friends who work in production (Knoxville is a big TV production town as it turns out), so it would be fun to put something together here. I don’t have any kind of vision, though, and doubt I could get everyone together to move on this until the idea of COVID as endemic is more normalized. Still, a guy can dream.</p>

<h4 id="a-digital-experience">A digital experience</h4>
<p>Augmented reality, NFTs, a professional-looking website! All this &amp; more is possible when you have insanely talented friends!</p>

<p>In this case, my buddy <a href="https://www.lookitsatravis.com">Travis Vignon</a> came up with a brilliant idea for moving my poems into the realm of AR. I won’t give anything away in case I don’t have the capacity to follow up on it, but I’ll just say it would be the most significant advancement in the world of poetics since WC Williams created an American form with his triadic line. More or less.</p>

<h4 id="open-mics">Open mics</h4>
<p>On November 14, I joined <a href="https://www.rattle.com/rattlecast">Rattlecast</a> for the first time. I remember, weeks ago, Rattle editor Timothy Green said he was surprised that so few poets took the opportunity to read their poems on the open mic. (<em>Rattle</em>, by the way, has one of the widest readerships of any literary journal.). So I finally joined for Ananda Lima’s feature, and plan to continue joining as a simple way to get my name out there.</p>

<p>You can hear me read &amp; briefly discuss my book &amp; <a href="https://youtu.be/wEvTt5KY1DE?list=PLD_fMFokoxAEbUzqLMIldRifEYrWK7w9-&amp;t=5405">my poem here</a>. (I hope this doesn’t count as “publication” to some. I’ll keep submitting it, regardless.)</p>

<h4 id="poetry-cafe">Poetry cafe</h4>
<p>Another friend, Joel Smith, teaches high school mathematics &amp; robotics in Knoxville. One of his colleagues in literature concludes a unit with a “poetry cafe”, where faculty can read/perform poems to the students. He asked my permission to read <a href="http://connotationpress.com/poetry/3102-andrew-p-dillon-poetry-2"><cite class="poem">Apologia of Having No Clear Answers</cite></a>, and did so this past week.</p>

<p>It’s hard to express how meaningful that is. That he thought of me first, and wanted to share something I wrote with his colleagues &amp; students, feels so good. It’s a poem dealing with solitude &amp; uncertainty, and he said he thought the students needed to hear it right now, as the institutions they should be able to rely on have crumbled around them in the last two years. As though what poets do matters! I know we all believe it does, but I’m grateful to feel that. He reported enthusiastic reception from the teacher &amp; librarian (who wants to carry my book in the school!) and attentive listeners among the students. He has a great voice and captivating presence, so I knew he would be a great reader of my (or anyone’s) poetry; he did confirm that the only Poet Voice came from other readers <em class="far fa-grin-tears"></em></p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
Is all this a bit ridiculous? Yes! I have no idea what I'm doing! Which is probably why it's still fun.
</div>

<h3 id="to-celebrate">To celebrate</h3>
<p>Earlier this year, I was talking to my therapist about the book &amp; my thoughts about completing such a huge project. I told him I had heard that artists often go through a depressive period afterward, and he told me that I should do two things when I finish:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Not</strong> start a new project, and instead take time to appreciate what I accomplished</li>
  <li>Do something to celebrate</li>
</ul>

<p>In that vein, when the booksite is finally live, I’m going to get a tattoo to celebrate. I’ve actually been trying to get an appointment with a Nashville artist, but she’s extremely popular, and her books have only been open for ~2 hours all year. I submitted through her website, but never got a response, so I’m gonna branch out and look for artists with a similar palette.</p>

<h2 id="sports">Sports</h2>
<p>I was wrong about the Sabres. They are bad! But the Vols are going bowling (I called that upset over Kentucky), and the Bills will (probably<em class="fas fa-question-circle"></em>) still win the division.</p>

<h3 id="bjj">BJJ</h3>
<p>Another week, another new injury (actually a couple weeks ago now)! We were practicing takedowns from the pummel position, which in this case included a hip toss. We train on mats, of course, but I guess I took one too many falls and, despite knowing how to fall correctly, I seem to have a bruised rib. Or maybe bruised intercostals? Either way, it hurt to take deep breaths.</p>

<p>Since this country is rhinestone-studded trash, I didn’t go to the doctor for imaging, because an x-ray would cost somewhere in the range of hundreds of dollars out of pocket. Hard to say, really, since those charges vary wildly and providers &amp; facilities don’t have to disclose those costs. So yeah, this whole system is really optimized for human beings.</p>

<h4 id="mat-culture">Mat culture</h4>
<p>I’m not sure if that’s a real phrase, but one thing I’ve been meaning to talk about is the vibe at martial arts gyms. You may or may not be surprised to hear that people who are learning how to attack &amp; manipulate the human body tend to be extremely careful practitioners. My not-insignificant experience is that people are constantly talking through what they’re doing, trying to help each other understand the theory underpinning the practice, &amp; apologizing for small mistakes.</p>

<p>I think apologizing is mostly a novice thing. As you get more comfortable, my sense is that you don’t really apologize for accidents (you’re in a gym learning to hurt people, after all), and also you simply make fewer mistakes. We know it wasn’t malicious; you’ll figure it out and do better. Plus, fighters are overwhelmingly supportive. Probably because, in our home gyms, we’re not competing with each other at all, so we just want to see everyone do well, even when they tap us.</p>

<p>And, maybe most surprising if you’ve never studied martial arts: <strong>People who know how to fight do not want to get into fights.</strong> For a couple reasons:</p>
<ul>
  <li>You don’t know what a stranger is capable of, or willing to do to you. Or if they have a weapon.</li>
  <li>Unless you can prove self-defense, you’ve got a greater legal obligation to moderate your body. “Lethal weapons” and all.</li>
</ul>

<p>I really don’t know how the law parses that latter point. I assume a novice like me has more latitude. For an advanced fighter, though, I’ve heard some devastating (anecdotal) accounts of people defending themselves, but serving prison time because they killed or severely injured an aggressor. I’m not pretending to be an expert, but what I learned to do (from Krav Maga) is:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Get away.<br />
If you can run away, do that first. No body gets hurt.</li>
  <li>Diffuse the situation.<br />
If it’s reasonable &amp; there’s enough time, saying something weird or silly (“The purple fences are missing their socks!”) can often confuse an aggressive person and break that hormonal spell. Then you get away.</li>
  <li>Fight, and be the first person to attack.<br />
If there is absolutely gonna be a fight, be the one to start &amp; end it. Then you get away.</li>
</ol>

<p>I’m a bigger guy, but I’m more afraid of a street fight now (as a reasonably capable fighter) than when I was 20 years old, 30 lbs lighter, and did not know how to handle my body. Even while I feel confident &amp; safe in almost any situation. It’s a weird dynamic. Definitely some poems in there.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="bjj" /><category term="publications" /><category term="tgp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I don’t know about the rest of you, but I’m tired of waiting for the mutant limbs I was guaranteed after getting my COVID vaccines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unincorporated Problems in the Late Bama Dynasty</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/unincorporatedProblems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unincorporated Problems in the Late Bama Dynasty" /><published>2021-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/unincorporated-posts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/unincorporatedProblems"><![CDATA[<p>At this point in the COVID timeline, my reckoning of time seems irreparably damaged. This week, my girlfriend Sarah &amp; I were browsing for a movie and settled on <cite class="movie">The Bourne Identity</cite>. A few minutes in, I said “Didn’t we watch this a few months ago?” She looked confused. “Maybe you did?” No, reader, I hadn’t watched it myself over the summer. We watched it together, but at her old apartment. Where she hasn’t lived for 18 months.<!-- here --></p>

<p>My usually precise memory has served me well as a writer. But the pandemic has felt like one long Sunday. I keep confusing the days of the week, which have all lost their feel. I imagine we all feel a bit unmoored in our lives now.</p>

<p>Anyway, here’s how my creative life is going:</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>Since lamenting my lack of motivation &amp; progress <a href="/updatesLatePatriarchy">a few posts ago</a>, I found a renewed wave of mental energy, and have been working steadily (if still slowly).</p>

<h3 id="tooltips">Tooltips</h3>
<p>I finished my first pass at adding tooltips into the poems. You most often see tooltips as text that becomes visible when you mouse-over some element on a webpage:</p>

<!-- tooltip screenshot -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/dopplerEffect.png" alt="
A screenshot of the poem 'Doppler Effect' from the author's in-progress book, showing an open tooltip on the word &lt;i&gt;Sunsphere&lt;/i&gt;, with the text &lt;q&gt;The symbol of the 1982 World's Fair, in Knoxville, TN&lt;/q&gt;
" style="max-width: 65%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 65%">
Originally published in <cite class="journal">The Bosphorus Review of Books</cite>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I haven’t been able to test on mobile yet, so I don’t know if you can tap the word to open the tooltip. I won’t include the CSS here because it’s 119 lines of code, but <a href="https://idratherbewriting.com/documentation-theme-jekyll/index.html">Tom</a> used the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">a</code> element to create this functionality. Or maybe this is built in to Bootstrap? It’s honestly beyond me. I can read the stylesheet and understand what’s happening, but I’m not yet skilled enough to have known how to begin iterating it.</p>

<p>I tried to be judicial in applying the tooltips. One potential drawback to implementing them is that they become a distraction to the poems. I didn’t want too many tooltips, or ones containing complex information, that would stop the reader in the middle of the poem and kick them out of the experience; and I didn’t want them to contain links that would entice readers to leave the poem. It’s an awesome feature than opens a lot of possibilities, but it can also work against me.</p>

<p>For a similar reason, it’s a good idea to minimize the number of inline links in technical documentation; one compromise is to collect links at the end of a page. Similarly, my book uses tabs below each poem to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>collect longer notes, digressions, &amp; links.</li>
  <li>compile a list of related poems (based on keywords).</li>
</ul>

<p>If the term can be easily looked up, I didn’t bother to include a tooltip or note for it. For example, “Betelgeuse” or “Kuiper Belt”. I also wanted to avoid explaining <em>everything</em>. There’s nothing wrong with expecting the reader to do a little research &amp; reflection after reading. I mean, if you’re not willing to engage deeply with a poem, why are you even reading?</p>

<h3 id="audio">Audio</h3>
<p>I finished recording scratch files for each poem. I used the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">audio</code> element to embed the recording below the poem title. Here’s the recording of <cite class="poem">Doppler Effect</cite>, the poem in the screenshot above:</p>

<audio display="block" controls="" controlsList="nodownload"> <source src="audio/dopplerEffect.m4a" /> Your browser doesn't support HTML5 audio. </audio>

<p>The recordings are very low-quality because I used my phone and then compressed those files to send over Bluetooth to my computer. Even though they’re very rough, I think I’m going to release the book with these recordings. My dad, who is a recording engineer, has offered to record them professionally, so I may take him up on that after the v1.0 release of the book.</p>

<h3 id="mvp">MVP</h3>
<p>Professional recordings are not on my plate right now because the booksite has already taken so much of my time &amp; energy over the past 13 months. I’m shooting for a <strong>Minimum Viable Product</strong>—a development strategy that introduces a new product with the minimum necessary features to get the user’s attention. Later, I can roll out new features to enhance the book. It’s a big advantage over print publishing, and part of this project is highlighting those advantages, so why wouldn’t I? As mentioned in <a href="/whatTweetsComeTo">an earlier post</a>, all my updates after 1.0 will be dev-related; I will not be editing, adding, or removing any poems (with the exceptions of typos &amp; coding errors).</p>

<p>As far as the poems go, I once heard <a href="https://www.mtsu.edu/faculty/gaylord-brewer">Gaylord Brewer</a> reference “the dust on the butterfly’s wings” as an argument for moderation in revision; meaning, when you get too far from the original inspiration/muse/angel/duende of the poem, your edits risk sanitizing the poem—degrading what gave the poem its magic. I think he was paraphrasing another author, but it definitely sounds like some poet shit. Which I agree with! For me (even before I’m done) the book is something of an artifact. As is each poem. They represent who I was/what I felt/what I understood at a particular point in time.</p>

<p>Walt Whitman, in contrast, edited <cite class="book">Leaves of Grass</cite> until he died. To edit a complete poem (especially after publication) feels like a transgressive form of revisionism. Even though I may have written wrong-headed, privileged, or just plain cringey poems in the past, I don’t want to edit them out of guilt or pride. Some of those poems I don’t ever submit; but for the ones that may have been published, they already reached an audience. To retroactively edit out my faults feels dishonest. For my writing. I’m not trying to restrict your process, of course.</p>

<p>So I’ll likely add a few features after I initially serve my site at <a href="https://www.thegreatpermission.com">thegreatpermission.com</a> (again, nothing there yet), but I won’t add or remove poems, revise any poems, or change the organization of the book after that first release.</p>

<h3 id="marketing-or-some-facsimile-thereof">Marketing (or some facsimile thereof)</h3>
<p><a href="/dreamCommonSub">Last post</a>, I talked a bit about figuring out how to promote the book. Since I work in techcom, which is often within or adjacent to marketing in a business org, I have a patchwork understanding of what’s necessary (the doc team at my first tech writing job was part of the marketing department). But what I know is very surface level, and based mostly on observation, not practice.</p>

<p>This feels like the biggest category of remaining work for the book. Should I have a budget for things like ads? Who should I ask to review my book, how do I initiate that request, how many reviewers do I need? Should I plan release events/readings, how many, should I try to plan a book tour (where I lose money)? I’ve found some resources to help me get started, and may request a consultation with one or two people I know who have worked in publishing.</p>

<p>In some ways, this is harder that writing &amp; organizing the book or building the website because I have next-to-no experience with this industry. Everything feels very abstract &amp; somewhat indecipherable. At least my professional life prepared me for front-end web development. Promoting the book is essential, and as a novice in the marketing world, am I hanging the biggest project of my life on my general ability to become proficient at new things?</p>

<p>I guess there’s no way around that risk. Becoming or building anything is risky because there are always opportunity costs. Though in that light, I suppose I’m not risking all that much. What would I be doing if I hadn’t continued to write poetry after college? Where would I put my energy? Somewhere within athletics, likely. But I’m 36 now, so my life as a competitive athlete would be basically over. Music is my next obvious passion. I gave up playing guitar a long time ago, but I’m in Nashville, and my dad is a writer, musician, &amp; engineer, so there’s a good chance I’d have picked up guitar or keyboards and tried to make it.</p>

<p>I have a series of poems in which I write to myself at different ages or across the multiverse to possible lives. I guess I have some new grist for that mill.</p>

<h3 id="writing-retreat">Writing retreat</h3>
<p>I’m taking PTO soon to work on all of this and more. I want to finish a few poems, but mostly focus on a handful of formatting &amp; tech issues for the book, and draft my marketing plan.</p>

<p>Here are the big work items I’m focusing on:</p>

<h4 id="poems">Poems</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Complete revisions on 5–6 poems I’ve planned to include, and record the audio</li>
  <li>Confirm my TOC</li>
  <li>Reach out to potential editors to discuss interest/availability/cost</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="tech-issues">Tech issues</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Resolve minor navigation &amp; scripting issues</li>
  <li>Finish adding tooltips, notes, &amp; the keywords that create the related poems lists</li>
  <li>Complete the workout pages<br />
Yes, the book will have workouts, like you’d do at the gym, and also some selected family recipes. The idea came to me while listening to <a href="https://www.commonpodcast.com/home/2019/11/18/episode-77-tina-chang">Rachel Zucker’s conversation with Tina Chang</a>.</li>
  <li>Place the interludes (which include the workouts &amp; recipes)</li>
  <li>Clean up the project tree<br />
There are a lot of files from Tom’s theme that I’m not using, and leaving them in bloats my repository.</li>
  <li>Optimize Google Analytics<br />
I have GA running on this site, but I really don’t know how to use it effectively.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="marketing">Marketing</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Draft an actual plan (research, competitive analysis, SWOT, goals, objectives, target markets, message, tactics, timeline, budget)<br />
This is a little weird, because I’m not marketing for a business or consumer product. I think not all of those categories will be directly relevant, but I do think it’ll be useful to think through my project with a business mind.</li>
  <li>Submit relentlessly to journals</li>
  <li>Make a list of people &amp; institutions who care about my writing, and draft a communication (a press release, I guess) to inform them of the book and ask them to share/mention it</li>
  <li>Make a list of people who might write about or interview me</li>
  <li>Get a professional head shot<br />
The one on my homepage is by the excellent <a href="https://www.instagram.com/colin.potts/">Colin Potts</a>, but it’s almost 8 years old now, and I have different hair.</li>
</ul>

<p>More on some or all of those in forthcoming posts!</p>

<h2 id="writing-poems">Writing poems</h2>
<p>Hasn’t been much of this in the past 13 months. However, last week my girlfriend was making apple butter &amp; cider, and she left the apple butter in the crock pot overnight. She went to work in the morning and asked me to stir it occasionally. When I walked into the kitchen to do that, the scent was so strong and, combined with the newly cold Fall air (and the little taste I took), it was a very intense sensory moment. I felt a poem come into me, and sat down to write it. I got a full draft in one sitting, which is unusual for me.</p>

<p>Last year, I adopted <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a> as my notetaking app. I’ve been using OneNote for years and still have tons of scraps there, but am slowly migrating over. Obsidian is gorgeous, with useful features like backlinking &amp; graph view. It’s freemium, but totally free for a local installation (sync is a premium feature). Since I haven’t been writing much, I hadn’t opened Obsidian in a while. After drafting this new poem, I read back through some old drafts—and wow! I’ve got some really good poems just waiting for a revision. I feel like I stumbled on this forgotten treasure, but it was always my treasure, and now I have more work to do.</p>

<h2 id="this-site">This site</h2>
<p>The biggest change is that I added a <a href="/now">Now page</a>. You can read about Now pages at <a href="https://nownownow.com/about">Derek Sivers website</a>, but essentially it’s a regularly updated page to inform visitors what you’ve been up to lately. In contrasts with <a href="/about">About</a> pages, which are a long shot on the author—the highlights. It may be redundant on a blog, but I think targets visitors who don’t want to read through a backlog of posts, but want to know a bit more about you.</p>

<p>You might notice some new formatting too. I got some feedback on my website in the form of a (very helpful) issue in my code repository. The end result is that images are now mobile-friendly, and the homepage has some text &amp; links so you don’t have to open the context menu to navigate.</p>

<p>In some root-level pages, I also styled some h2 headers with this label:</p>
<h2 id="header"><span class="label label-info">Header!</span></h2>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"label label-info"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Header!<span class="nt">&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It’s not good design on my part. They look like buttons, which should be interactive. I’ll fix that eventually, but I thought the site needed something to break up the monotony of black text on a white page, and this was already in the stylesheet.</p>

<h2 id="sports-stuff">Sports stuff</h2>
<p>Being active is probably my first priority, along with work. They’re like priorities 1A &amp; 1B (work because, in a capitalist, Puritanical America, it’s almost impossible for it not to consume your waking life unless you’re independently wealthy). When I miss just a week of exercise, there’s nothing checking my depression &amp; anxiety. If I didn’t exercise, I don’t think I’d be mentally well enough to write or maintain close personal relationships. Right now, my primary activity is Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu.</p>

<h3 id="bjj">BJJ</h3>
<p>As I mention in the current iteration of my <a href="/now">Now</a> page, I’ve been practicing Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu since June; and I suffered another injury just before my birthday in August (a tradition for me)—a sprained ligament in my wrist. That’s reasonably healed now, so I’m back to sparring in my BJJ classes (or “rolling” as we call it).</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
  <p>I'm a beginner to BJJ, which is a very complicated discipline, full of nuance.</p>
  <p>Please contextualize my observations &amp; opinions as those of someone who understands very little.</p>
</div>

<p>I’m a fairly athletic person. I pick up most sports very quickly, unless there’s significant sport-specific skill (for example, developing your handle in basketball). To some extent, that translates to BJJ; I move quickly and my instincts are decent. But the technical aspect is unreal. I’ve never experienced any athletics with so much theory (for lack of a better word) to learn. In every situation/position you find yourself in, there are new offensive &amp; defensive techniques to learn. Since there’s no real limit to the number of positions your body can be in, there’s kind of a limitless number of techniques to learn. At least, that’s how it feels to me now as a fairly fresh white belt. There are, of course, foundational movements &amp; techniques; I just haven’t developed that muscle memory yet.</p>

<p>Speaking of belts, I only practice no-gi (I don’t wear the thick cotton jacket &amp; pants, sometimes called a “kimono”). I don’t think there’s a belt system, and strictly speaking, it may not even be considered jiu-jitsu. So, I may be more accurately described as a “grappler” than a “jiu-jitsuka”.</p>

<h3 style="color: #FF8200;" id="tennessee-vols-football">Tennessee Vols football</h3>
<p>They were exciting there for a minute! The new hurry-up offense under Josh Heupel is fun to watch, but (we’ve been saying this for 12 years), the team lacks depth.</p>

<p>It’s not unexpected to see a new coach have limited success during his grace period—Tennessee’s first half against Alabama is a nice microcosm. Can his staff recruit &amp; develop talent, and win meaningful games? No UT coach has since Fulmer (except the two times Butch Jones beat Georgia and the one time he beat Florida). That said, at 4–4 with games against South Alabama &amp; Vanderbilt still to come, they should make a bowl game. I think they might beat Kentucky too.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-ut">
  <h4 id="we-got-there-first">We got there first</h4>
 For any Texas alumni, I refer to Tennessee as <strong>UT</strong> because my school is almost a century older than yours.
</div>

<p>Nick Saban has to retire one of these days, right? Until then, I expect my Vols to be irrelevant; if they’re on a similar trajectory as the Buffalo Bills, Heupel is our coach of the future, and Saban will retire after next season to usher in the Vols return to competitive football.</p>

<h3 id="buffalo-bills">Buffalo Bills</h3>
<p>I love <a href="https://www.espn.com/nfl/recap?gameId=401326422">the call</a>.</p>

<p>The Bills are 5–2 after beating the Dolphins for the second time, and will win the AFC East barring a massive implosion or injury to Josh Allen. I don’t worry about implosions anymore, because Sean McDermott is one of the best coaches in the league.</p>

<p>I just heard every Bills fan collectively groan, but I also don’t worry about jinxes anymore. Nothing any sports team does will affect my life, and nothing I do can affect the outcome of any game. You’ll be so much happier if you internalize that. To be fair, I internalized it the hard way, progressively, as a Bills fan from 1990–2016.</p>

<h3 id="buffalo-sabres">Buffalo Sabres</h3>
<p>They’re good this year! Or, at least, definitely Not Bad. They’ve started the season 5-1-1 with a +9 GD, and despite the Jack Eichel drama (a young, generational talent who was stripped of his captaincy before the season amid trade rumors), they seem to have pulled it together under a new coach.</p>

<p>This is amazing since they’ve been a bottom-5 team for a full decade.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="bjj" /><category term="buffaloBills" /><category term="marketing" /><category term="personal" /><category term="techJourney" /><category term="tgp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At this point in the COVID timeline, my reckoning of time seems irreparably damaged. This week, my girlfriend Sarah &amp; I were browsing for a movie and settled on The Bourne Identity. A few minutes in, I said “Didn’t we watch this a few months ago?” She looked confused. “Maybe you did?” No, reader, I hadn’t watched it myself over the summer. We watched it together, but at her old apartment. Where she hasn’t lived for 18 months.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dream of a Common Submission</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/dreamCommonSub" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dream of a Common Submission" /><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/the-dream-common-sub</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/dreamCommonSub"><![CDATA[<p>Not long after I started working professionally as a Technical Writer, I decided to design a content strategy that would eliminate Microsoft Word from my personal writing. What I’ve got now works fairly well. It’s much more streamlined than my previous setup using Word, but there are several areas where I’d like to improve.<!-- here --></p>

<h2 id="why-not-word">Why not Word?</h2>
<p>Microsoft as a whole manages to cling to this status as a suite of indispensable tools despite being entirely outclassed by other (free) products. I could point out many more problems I have with Word, but I’ll restrain myself to only those related to the topic of this post—Submissions.</p>

<h3 id="word-doesnt-modularize">Word doesn’t modularize</h3>
<p>Meaning you can’t easily break the things you write into smaller pieces to reuse in multiple places. Your submissions likely contain several identical pieces of content:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Your contact info</li>
  <li>The date</li>
  <li>A short bio</li>
</ul>

<p>Maybe a few others. If you’re typing them out each time, you introduce the possibility of typos, inconsistencies, errors, or oversights. Even copy &amp; pasting those items from a master document is an unnecessary use of time, and could result in unintended styling if you forget to correct it when Word pastes the wrong font or indentation into your document.</p>

<p>Word does have Quick Parts &amp; Auto Text that can reuse chunks of content, but they’re unsurprisingly difficult to store &amp; edit. And worst of all, they only work on your local installation of Word; the reusable content you create isn’t available globally.</p>

<p>That last part is probably only a concern for professional writers who need to share repositories with other authors, or people using virtual machines. If you’re gonna continue using Word, look into Quick Parts &amp; Auto Text to make you writing life a bit easier.</p>

<h3 id="no-distinction-between-presentation--semantics">No distinction between presentation &amp; semantics</h3>
<p>Word uses a proprietary markup (just a custom XML, I think) to code the content you add to a document. If you’ve ever copied something from Word and pasted it into a different program, you’ve probably seen the jumbled markup that Word applies.</p>

<p>This is a problem when you need to copy &amp; paste poems into a submission document. Word has a feature called Styles that creates semi-separation between your content &amp; how it appears. But even using Styles and copying a poem from one Word document to another, your formatting is rarely preserved.</p>

<h3 id="version-control-is-a-nightmare">Version control is a nightmare</h3>
<p>Briefly, version control is a method of tracking &amp; managing changes to source files. “Source files” could be:</p>
<ul>
  <li>files that build a website (like HTML, CSS, &amp; Javascript).</li>
  <li>files that create an app (Java, Rust, etc.).</li>
  <li>any other document (Word, PDF, etc.).</li>
</ul>

<p>A version control system (VCS) tracks every modification to the source files, and allows you to access any earlier version of those files. The industry standard VCS is <a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a>. It can get extremely complicated, but if you set up &amp; utilize a Git repo, you can feel confident that you’ll never lose anything you commit to the repo.</p>

<p>But you can’t really track Microsoft documents (Word, Excel, etc.) with Git because of their proprietary markup. Git <em>will</em> save those files, but you can’t see the character-by-character changes you can with plaintext files. Which means if you wanted to find a previous version of a poem, you wouldn’t be able to tell which version you wanted with Git. If you don’t use a VCS, you probably have a dozen files for each poem, with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_v#</code> appended to the filename, and you still have to open each one to find the historical version you’re looking for.</p>

<p>Dropbox has a version control feature, but it’s premium. Google Drive includes versioning for free! Though I’m not sure how well it works or how easy it is to use.</p>

<p>It’s possible to set up a workable version control scenario with Word, but you need:</p>
<ul>
  <li>to be the only author (probably true).</li>
  <li>access to Sharepoint (it’s not free).</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="theres-a-better-open-source-tool-for-that">There’s a better (open source) tool for that</h3>
<p>Whatever you want to do with Word, there’s an easier, more efficient tool that’s probably free. In terms of submitting your poems, there’s no need to pay for Word when Google Docs &amp; LibreOffice can save as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.docx</code>.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-warning">
<em class="far fa-thumbs-up"></em> Editors, I am simply begging you to accept submissions in at least one format that is not Microsoft Word.
</div>

<h2 id="submission-architecture">Submission architecture</h2>
<p>I don’t know much at all about web development, just enough to make my website run, which I learned <em>in order to</em> make it run.</p>

<p>In the case of my current submission architecture (which I’ll refer to as my “localhost setup”), I used <a href="https://medium.com/@JohnFoderaro/how-to-set-up-apache-in-macos-sierra-10-12-bca5a5dfffba">this guide by John Foderaro</a> to get started. I doubt I would’ve figured it out on my own, or even had the patience to try. (Although I think I had to play around with some of the configurations, and I definitely used TextEdit—nano is atrocious to work in.)</p>

<p>Below is a detailed look at how I use HTML, CSS, PHP, &amp; Apache to store poems and create journal submissions.</p>
<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
  <p><strong>HTML</strong> is the markup language that the web is written in; it defines the structure of your website &amp; pages.</p>
  <p><strong>CSS</strong> defines what your HTML looks like.</p>
  <p><strong>PHP</strong> is a server-side scripting language; meaning, your server interprets the code.<br /> (Javascript is a client-side scripting language, so your browser processes the code, just like it processes HTML &amp; CSS when you navigate to a website.)</p>
  <p><strong>Apache</strong> is an open-source server. At the most basic level, a server accepts requests from a client (your browser) and responds with the content it's storing (a website).<br /> Apache is built in to Macs, so I just had to turn it on using the guide I mentioned above.</p>
</div>

<h3 id="poems">Poems</h3>
<p>I use a very simple file that I titled <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">poemTemplate.html</code> to write &amp; save each poem. It’s not, strictly speaking, a template because I have to <kbd>command</kbd> + <kbd>shift</kbd> + <kbd>S</kbd> to save; it’s possible I could create templates in my editor (<a href="https://atom.io">Atom</a>), but I haven’t taken the time to look in to it.</p>

<p>I save each poem at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/Users/&lt;username&gt;/Sites/poems</code> (on Mac), which you can access in Finder when you want to edit a file, or view in your browser by navigating to <kbd>localhost/~username/poems</kbd> (where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">poems</code> is a directory you add after setup). You want to use your browser to view because that forces the server &amp; browser to run all your code (like CSS, PHP, Javascript, etc.).</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</span>

<span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;title&gt;</span>Title<span class="nt">&lt;/title&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;meta</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">"viewport"</span> <span class="na">content=</span><span class="s">"width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;link</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"../poemStyle.css"</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"text/css"</span> <span class="na">rel=</span><span class="s">"stylesheet"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;link</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"../fonts/KohinoorBangla.ttc"</span> <span class="na">rel=</span><span class="s">"stylesheet"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;link</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Montserrat"</span> <span class="na">rel=</span><span class="s">"stylesheet"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/head&gt;</span>

<span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;h3&gt;</span>Title<span class="nt">&lt;/h3&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;p</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"epigraph"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Epigraph<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>Body<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;p</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"dedication"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Dedication<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s what happening in that file:</p>

<table>
  <colgroup>
    <col width="35%" />
    <col width="65%" />
  </colgroup>
  <tr>
    <th><code>!DOCTYPE</code></th>
    <td>Tells the browser what version of HTML the file uses.<br /><br />
    For HTML<i class="fab fa-html5"></i>, the current version of HTML, it's the very simple <code>!DOCTYPE html</code> you see above. It was more complicated for older versions.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><code>head</code> &amp; metadata elements</th>
    <td>Contains metadata elements—elements about the document:<br /><br />
    <b><code>title</code></b><br />
    The name of the document, which appears in the brower's title bar or page tab.<br /><br />
    <b><code>meta name="viewport" …</code></b><br />
    Tells the browser how to control the page's dimensions. Essentially, it sets the width of the page to the screen-width of the device displaying it, so you can view on desktops, laptops, tablets, &amp; phones.<br /><br />
    <b><code>link</code></b><br />
    Creates a relationship between the current document and an external one. In this case, I'm linking to my stylesheet so my CSS is applied to the poem, and to some fonts I like. "KohinoorBangla" is a font on my computer; the other is one Google makes available for free at that URL.<br /><br />
    There are many other elements that could appear here.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><code>body</code> &amp; text elements</th>
    <td>Contains everything that actually gets rendered in a browser.<br /><br />
    The header &amp; paragraph tags are pretty straight-forward. Two <code>p</code> elements include classes; those classes are defined in my stylesheet to look a certain way (dedications are indented &amp; italic; epigraphs are right-aligned &amp; italic).</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>Depending on how I want a poem to look, it can get fairly complicated to tag it and apply the correct CSS. I won’t get into specifics here, but I’ll say that in my experience, it’s less complicated to get HTML &amp; CSS to do what you want than MS Word. Plus, if you supply someone with your HTML poem &amp; stylesheet, they’ll see exactly what you intended, which you can’t always say for Word, even when you’re both using the same version of Word.</p>

<h3 id="submission-documents">Submission documents</h3>
<p>Of course, no journal I’ve ever seen accepts submissions of HTML documents. So my final output is always to PDF.</p>

<p>This file is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">submissionTemplate.php</code>:</p>

<div class="language-php highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;title&gt;</span>JOURNAL poetry submission<span class="nt">&lt;/title&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;meta</span> <span class="na">charset=</span><span class="s">"utf-8"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;meta</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">"author"</span> <span class="na">content=</span><span class="s">"Andrew P. Dillon"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;link</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"../../poemStyle.css"</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"text/css"</span> <span class="na">rel=</span><span class="s">"stylesheet"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;link</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"../../fonts/Kohinoor"</span> <span class="na">rel=</span><span class="s">"stylesheet"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;link</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Montserrat"</span> <span class="na">rel=</span><span class="s">"stylesheet"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/head&gt;</span>

<span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
  <span class="c">&lt;!-- CONTACT --&gt;</span>
  <span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../contactInfo.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>

  <span class="c">&lt;!-- JOURNAL --&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;p</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"journal"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>JOURNAL poetry submission<span class="nt">&lt;br</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
  <span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="nb">date_default_timezone_set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'America/Chicago'</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">print</span> <span class="nb">date</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"d M Y"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nb">time</span><span class="p">());</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>

  <span class="c">&lt;!-- TOC --&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;h4&gt;</span>Contents<span class="nt">&lt;/h4&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;ul&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#coverLetter"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Cover letter<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#poem1"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Poem1<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#poem2"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Poem2<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#poem3"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Poem3<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#poem4"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Poem4<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#poem5"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Poem5<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;li&gt;&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"#bio"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Author bio<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;/ul&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>

  <span class="c">&lt;!-- COVER LETTER --&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"coverLetter"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../coverLetter.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

  <span class="c">&lt;!-- POEMS --&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"poem1"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../poems/.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"poem2"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../poems/.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"poem3"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../poems/.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"poem4"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../poems/.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"poem5"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../poems/.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

  <span class="c">&lt;!-- BIO --&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"page-break"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"bio"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  	<span class="cp">&lt;?php</span> <span class="k">include</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"../../shortBio.html"</span><span class="p">);</span> <span class="cp">?&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It needs to be a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.php</code> file so the server will parse the PHP commands (the date declaration &amp; includes). <em>Includes</em>, btw, are exactly what they sound like—they navigate to the file I specify and insert everything in that file into my submission document. That way, I only have to maintain:</p>
<ul>
  <li>one file for contact info.</li>
  <li>one of each poem.</li>
  <li>one short bio.</li>
</ul>

<p>In my profession, we call this “single-sourcing”.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
<em class="fa fa-info-circle"></em> I'm not including the CSS here because that file is lengthy &amp; unwieldy, and I don't want to try to explain the use cases for each class.
</div>

<h3 id="workflow">Workflow</h3>
<p>To bring it all together, here are the steps I take to create a submission document:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Open the template and enter submission info:
    <ol>
      <li>In the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">head</code> element &amp; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">JOURNAL</code> section, replace the <strong>JOURNAL</strong> placeholder with the name of the journal I’m submitting to.</li>
      <li>In the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">TOC</code> section, copy &amp; paste the titles of each poem.</li>
      <li>Probably delete the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">COVER LETTER</code> section because cover letters are unnecessary.<br />
 (More on this in a <a href="/greatFireblog">future post</a>.)</li>
      <li>In the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">POEM</code> section, enter the filename of each poem in front of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.html</code>.</li>
      <li>Type <kbd>command</kbd> + <kbd>shift</kbd> + <kbd>S</kbd> to Save As.
 <br /><br /></li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Create a PDF:
    <ol>
      <li>In my browser, navigate to the folder where I save my submissions: <kbd>localhost/~username/submissions</kbd>.</li>
      <li>Open the file I just created.</li>
      <li>Right click and select <strong>Print page</strong>.<br />
 Make sure to right click on some negative space (not on any text), or else you’ll create a file with only what’s highlighted.</li>
      <li>In the <em>Print</em> dialog, select <strong>Save as PDF</strong>, and choose a location to save.<br />
 The specifics here depend on which browser you’re using. Safari seems to work best. Chrome works too. Brave does not.
 <br /><br /></li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Open the newly-created PDF and add page numbers.<br />
This is an Adobe premium feature now, but I have an old version of Acrobat Pro. I haven’t found a way to create page numbers with markup alone; although <a href="https://www.pagedjs.org/">paged.js</a> seems promising.</li>
</ol>

<p>Here’s the cover page of the PDF I end up submitting:
<!-- pdf output screenshot --></p>
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/pdfOutput.png" alt="A screenshot of an example PDF generated by my localhost submission workflow. It contains author contact info, the name of the journal I'm submitting to, the date, and a hyperlinked list of the poems it contains." style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
A very simple submission document
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Unfortunately, some journals that I <em>really</em> want to submit to still only accept <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.docx</code> files, so I do occasionally use Word. If you’re a student or work for a big enough company, you can usually get a discount on MS Office. At my previous employer, I think I upgraded to my current version for like $10. Of course, Office365 is a web subscription model now. I had to edit OneNote in the browser a couple times, and it’s essentially unusable. I can’t imagine a browser-based Word editor isn’t flaming garbage.</p>

<h2 id="room-for-improvement">Room for improvement</h2>
<p>You can probably see that a lot of the process is still somewhat manual &amp; tedious. And considering I’m writing a book using a static site generator, which has <em>its own</em> repository of poems, I am still duplicating effort in a major way. Here are some ways I’d like to streamline:</p>

<h3 id="true-single-sourcing-with-submodules">True single-sourcing with submodules</h3>
<p>The biggest problem I have is maintaining multiple copies of each poem. Right now I have <em>three</em> poetry directories:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The localhost setup I detailed in this post</li>
  <li>The <a href="https://idratherbewriting.com/documentation-theme-jekyll/index.html">custom Jekyll</a> project for my manuscript, <em><a href="/tgp">The Great Permission</a></em> (which only includes the poems that are actually in the book)</li>
  <li>A default <a href="https:jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a> project called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">poetry</code> (which I don’t keep updated, but is meant to replace the localhost setup when I finally implement submodules)</li>
</ul>

<p>Plus, I have this Jekyll project, the one that hosts this blog. Obviously, it doesn’t currently include any poems, but I’d like to one day add a <a href="/read">Read</a> page that compiles poems that were published a while ago or aren’t available online.</p>

<p><a href="https://michaelcurrin.github.io/dev-cheatsheets/cheatsheets/version-control/git/submodules">Michael Currin</a>, who seems to be the most active contributor on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com">Jekyll Talk</a>, pointed me to one of his projects that explain submodules &amp; how to implement them. I just haven’t taken the time to research the topic in-depth. I have read his About page, which includes this advice:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>I would avoid trying to make commits of new content in [the submodule] directly. Rather make them in the external repo in a different part of your machine or on GitHub, then update your submodule and commit the new reference.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Wait, so… once I create the relationship between an external repo &amp; a submodule, I can’t update the submodule? I feel like I must be misinterpreting that. I need the submodule to contain all my poems, and be contained within two external repos (my manuscript project &amp; this project). And as I edit, I’ll need to make new commits to the submodule of poems. So if that complicates the situation to enough of a degree, I may have to find another solution.</p>

<div class="bs-callout bs-callout-info">
<em class="fa fa-info-circle"></em> A "commit" is Git's terminology for content you save to your repo.
</div>

<p>“Well,” you may be saying, “if Git is such a pain in the ass, [reader, it truly is] then why not try some other VCS?” Fair question. Git is one problem, and I have another:</p>

<h4 id="git-is-a-necessary-evil">Git is a necessary evil</h4>
<p>Github Pages <em>requires</em> Git. Jekyll was created my Github’s cofounder, and has free, built-in support for GitHub Pages, which hosts my site. Right now, I just pay for the domains to <a href="/index.html">this site</a> &amp; my book. If I didn’t want to use Git, I’d have to find another host.</p>

<p>To be fair, Git is probably the best VCS out there. It’s just insanely complicated because it’s solving insanely complicated problems. Ideally, you wouldn’t have to be aware of your VCS—it would just work, the way Dropbox works without you thinking much about it beyond the initial setup. But Git forces you to interact with it in order for it to do anything; and its commands are complicated &amp; unintuitive.</p>

<h4 id="jekyll-is-feature-complete">Jekyll is “feature-complete”(?)</h4>
<p>That is, its future is uncertain, and the project may no longer be under active development. The primary contributor <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/news/2021/09/14/goodbye-dear-frank/">died suddenly</a>, and there’s been a lot of speculation about who, if anyone, will maintain the project. Reading some other articles about this, maybe the concern has been overblown. But if there <em>are</em> no devs, then it’s only a matter of time before Jekyll won’t be safe to use. It’s a Ruby gem, and needs to be updated to support recent Ruby releases for security.</p>

<p>Right now, I’m not going to worry about this. I’ve invested too much time &amp; effort into Jekyll &amp; this toolchain to make a huge change now.</p>

<h3 id="page-level-variables">Page-level variables</h3>
<p>Looking at the localhost setup in isolation, the only real issue is that I still have to copy &amp; paste a decent amount. In contrast, with a Jekyll project, <a href="https://shopify.dev/api/liquid">Liquid</a> allows me to access variables on the pages I’m targeting so they’re auto-filled in each document.</p>

<p>For example, here’s what my submission template could look like in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">poetry</code> project:</p>

<div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
author: "Andrew P. Dillon"
title: "JOURNAL poetry submission"
date: 2021-12-01
dateModified: 2021-12-01
layout: submission
categories: template
tags:
poem1: apologiaNoAnswers
poem2: todayYouWillDie
poem3: forgingTheBoy
---
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem1</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">where</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"permalink"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"{{poem1}}"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem2</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">where</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"permalink"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"{{poem2}}"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem3</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">where</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"permalink"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"{{poem3}}"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

&lt;body&gt;
  &lt;!-- CONTACT --&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">include</span><span class="w"> </span>contactInfo.md<span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

  &lt;!-- JOURNAL --&gt;
  &lt;p id="journal"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;br /&gt;
  <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"now"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">date</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"%d %b %Y"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;!-- TOC --&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Contents&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#coverLetter"&gt;Cover Letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#poem1"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">poem1</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#poem2"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">poem2</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#poem3"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">poem3</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#bio"&gt;Bio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;!-- COVER LETTER --&gt;
  &lt;div class="page-break" id="coverLetter"&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">include</span><span class="w"> </span>coverLetter.md<span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;!-- POEMS --&gt;
  &lt;div class="page-break" id="poem1"&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem1</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">content</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;div class="page-break" id="poem2"&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem2</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">content</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;div class="page-break" id="poem3"&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem3</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">poem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">content</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;!-- BIO --&gt;
  &lt;div class="page-break" id="bio"&gt;
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">include</span><span class="w"> </span>shortBio.md<span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The variables streamline everything. In this case, all I need to do is:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Open the template and fill out the YAML frontmatter (the top of the document, between the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">---</code>).</li>
  <li>On the command line, navigate to the project and serve the site: <kbd>bundle exec jekyll serve</kbd>.</li>
  <li>Navigate to the submission in my browser (it also gets a localhost address), and save a PDF as described above.</li>
</ol>

<p>I could also set some of those YAML variables as default values (like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">author</code> &amp; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">layout</code>) in the config file, so I wouldn’t have to include them in each file. And there are ways to automate creating PDFs, but all I know of, like PrinceXML, are paid. Pandoc might be able to handle it, but it seems very complicated. Jekyll might be able to do some post-processing using <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/plugins/hooks">hooks</a>, but again, I haven’t looked into it yet.</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>Setting all this up is pretty complicated—especially the Jekyll projects, and especially if you’re not familiar with any markup or scripting languages. It’s a big effort, both in terms of time &amp; mental energy. But then again, so is writing poetry &amp; submitting <em class="far fa-eye"></em></p>

<p>The good news is, like many open source projects, there’s a large community of people who have documented common use cases &amp; issues and who are willing to help. You also end up saving a lot of time &amp; energy in the long-run when you leave behind proprietary software.</p>

<p>Feel free to drop me a line if you’re a poet who needs a push in the open source direction!</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="submissions" /><category term="techJourney" /><category term="troubleshooting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Not long after I started working professionally as a Technical Writer, I decided to design a content strategy that would eliminate Microsoft Word from my personal writing. What I’ve got now works fairly well. It’s much more streamlined than my previous setup using Word, but there are several areas where I’d like to improve.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Tweets Come To</title><link href="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/whatTweetsComeTo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Tweets Come To" /><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/what-tweets-come-to</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andrewdillonpoetry.com/whatTweetsComeTo"><![CDATA[<p>Poetry Twitter blew up this month, and I’ve got cold takes. <!-- here -->But first, some updates.</p>

<h2 id="the-booksite">The booksite</h2>
<p>I finally made a bit of progress on the book (website? webbook? booksite?). After lamenting my lack of motivation in <a href="/updatesLatePatriarchy">the previous post</a>, I forced myself to open Atom and boldly continue to fail to understand a watered down scripting language.</p>

<h3 id="nested-iteration">Nested iteration</h3>
<p>On my “Acknowledgements” page, I wanted to call out previously published poems &amp; the journals they appeared in. The frontmatter of each individual poem includes the following variables (among many others):</p>
<div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  <span class="na">title</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">Apologia</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">of</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">a</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">God</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">Who</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">Abandoned</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">Its</span><span class="nv"> </span><span class="s">Creation"</span>
  <span class="na">publishedFlag</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">true"</span>
  <span class="na">journal</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">Stirring"</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>But even though I basically have a bachelor’s &amp; a master’s in abstraction, I guess I don’t grasp the kind of abstraction that programmers need, because it took me an embarrassing amount of time to figure out how to dynamically generate a list of published poems per journal.</p>

<p>Here’s the code that worked:</p>

<div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">pub</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">where</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"publishedFlag"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"true"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">sort</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"journal"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">pubList</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">pub</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">map</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"journal"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">uniq</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">sortedPoems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">poems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">where</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"publishedFlag"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"true"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">sort</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"title"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

&lt;table&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">pubList</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;ul&gt;<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">p</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">sortedPoems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">p</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">journal</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">p</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="p">}}</span>"&gt;<span class="p">{{</span><span class="nv">p</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
&lt;/table&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I can’t generate the output here because it’s in a different repository (I haven’t attempted to understand <a href="https://michaelcurrin.github.io/dev-cheatsheets/cheatsheets/version-control/git/submodules">Git submodules</a> yet), but here’s a screenshot:
<!-- Acknowledgements/previously published screenshot --></p>
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/tgp_pubs.png" alt="A partial list of journals &amp; the poems they published that will appear in the author's manuscript" style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
Definitely feel like a genius for coding some nested iterations.<br />This took me <em>days</em>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Here’s what’s going on:</p>
<table>
  <colgroup>
    <col width="20%" />
    <col width="80%" />
  </colgroup>
  <tr>
    <th><code>assign</code></th>
    <td>Creates a new variable, and allows you to filter &amp; sort results, which other tags (like <code>for</code> &amp; <code>if</code>) don't allow.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><code>site.poems</code></th>
    <td>"Poems" is the name of a <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/collections/"><i>Collection</i></a> I created. Jekyll allows you to access any collection with that <code>site.[collection]</code> notation.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><code>map</code></th>
    <td>Takes the attribute you specify ("journal", a frontmatter variable) and creates an array. I don't know a precise definition for "array", but I think of them as lists that programming languages can read.<br /><br />
    <code>uniq</code> is an array filter, so I had to create an array before I could use it to eliminate duplicates (because some journals took more than one poem).</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><code>for</code> loop</th>
    <td>Repeatedly executes whatever is between <code>{% for %}</code> &amp; <code>{% endfor %}</code>. The string immediately after "for" is a variable you create to access a directory, file, or another variable (in this case, the variables "pubList" &amp; "sortedPoems" I specified above).<br /><br />
    There are two <code>for</code> loops: the first one creates a table row for each journal and a <code>ul</code> to contain the poem titles; the second is within the <code>ul</code> and creates (with the <code>{% if %}</code> statement) a list item for each poem published in that journal.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><code>if</code> statement</th>
    <td>Executes whatever is between <code>{% if %}</code> &amp; <code>{% endif %}</code> when the specified condition is <code>true</code>.<br /><br />
    In this case, I'm using the <code>if</code> statement to ensure the only poems that get output are those whose <code>journal</code> frontmatter variable matches the array item from "pubList". If I removed the <code>if</code> statement, I'd get a list of <b>every</b> poem for which <code>publishedFlag: true</code> in <b>every</b> table row.</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>I’m not sure I like the alternating highlighted table rows, though. I’ll have to dig into the CSS files to figure out what’s creating that so I can turn it off.</p>

<h3 id="previousnext-buttons">Previous/Next buttons</h3>
<p>I’ve figured out what my problem is, but I’m no closer to solving it. As I’ve mentioned before, I want each page to have buttons that point to the previous page &amp; the next page so readers don’t have to use the sidebar navigation to get to every page. (I may also try to add Javascript keyboard shortcuts to allow navigation with the <em class="fa fa-arrow-left fa-1x"></em> &amp; <em class="fa fa-arrow-right fa-1x"></em> keys.) Without the styles in my book, they look something like this:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em class="fa fa-arrow-left fa-lg"></em> <a href=""><span class="label label-primary">Previous</span></a></td>
      <td><a href="https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" class="twitter-share-button" data-via="DillonAndrewP" data-show-count="true">Tweet</a>        <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</td>
      <td><a href=""><span class="label label-primary">Next</span></a> <em class="fa fa-arrow-right fa-lg"></em></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>But I can’t figure out how to generate the buttons with the correct URLs. The URLs that get output are always the URL of the current page. I expected this logic (not to mention dozens of variations of it) to work:</p>

<div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">site.data.sidebars.mydoc_sidebar.entries</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">folder</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">item.folders</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">for</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">folderitem</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">in</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">folder.folderitems</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">folderitem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">folderitem</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisPage</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nb">forloop.index</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"0"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">prevPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">minus</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"1"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">nextPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">thisPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">plus</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"1"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
        &lt;strong&gt;This page index: <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nb">forloop.index</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>, <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">page</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">remove</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"/"</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Prev page index: <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">prevPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>, <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">prevPage</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>, <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">prevPage</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">relative_url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Next page index: <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">nextPage</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>, <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">nextPage</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">title</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>, <span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">nextPage</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">relative_url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>&lt;/strong&gt;
        <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">break</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
      <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kr">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
    <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
  <span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
<span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endfor</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>

&lt;div class="container"&gt;
  &lt;div class="row"&gt;
    &lt;div class="col-sm-4"&gt;
      &lt;i class="fa fa-arrow-left fa-lg"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">prevPage</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>"&gt;&lt;span class="label label-primary"&gt;Previous&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class="col-sm-4"&gt;
      &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" class="twitter-share-button" data-via="DillonAndrewP" data-show-count="true"&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class="col-sm-4"&gt;
      &lt;a href="<span class="p">{{</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">nextPage</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nv">url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">}}</span>"&gt;&lt;span class="label label-primary"&gt;Next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;i class="fa fa-arrow-right fa-lg"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;strong&gt;</code> tags contain some logic I found to help identify my problem; here’s some example output:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>This page index: 6, viscosity.html<br />
Prev page index: -1, ,<br />
Next page index: 1, ,</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The blanks after “-1” &amp; “1” <em>should</em> be a title &amp; URL. Meaning my logic isn’t even accessing the YAML mapping in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mydoc_sidebar</code>.</p>

<p>So. If you happen to know a solution, reply to <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/t/how-can-i-create-previous-next-buttons-from-yaml-table-of-contents/6423">the issue I opened on Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>

<h3 id="going-forward">Going forward</h3>
<p>I don’t want to let some of these non-critical issues to keep me from releasing the book. The site builds, and you can navigate using the sidebar. I’m gonna try to update the site after the 1.0 release to add new features like:</p>
<ul>
  <li>previous/next buttons</li>
  <li>dark theme</li>
  <li>a prettier picture gallery</li>
  <li>professionally recorded audio for each poem (my dad has a studio!)</li>
</ul>

<p>Since I’m almost certainly self-publishing, I need a plan for how to promote the book. How will I make people aware that my book exists? Targeted ads? Contact friends, editors, &amp; important people in my literary spaces? Book launch event(s)? I have no idea right now. This is probably the biggest gap I face by not pursuing more traditional first book publication.</p>

<p>Finally, I need an editor! I have a few people in mind who I think would be excellent critical eyes for the poems &amp; the collection as a whole. When I have some kind of marketing plan in place, I’ll reach out to see if I can afford to hire them.</p>

<h2 id="world-on-fire">World on fire</h2>
<p>The tweet that divided us:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet">
  <p lang="en" dir="ltr">I wish poets understood that the general population has no interest in what we do, so when we speak we are speaking only to each other. The delusion that poetry is something powerful is a straight line to all kinds of toxic positivities that are really just us lying to ourselves.</p>
— Danielle Rose (@danirosepoet) <a href="https://twitter.com/danirosepoet/status/1433816027947839494?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 3, 2021</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>If you read the replies, there are a handful of thoughtful people engaging sincerely. But mostly I saw frustrated poets leaving incredulous replies about how much poetry has affected their lives &amp; the lives of people they know. In other words, they willfully misread her tweet.</p>

<h3 id="see-for-yourself">See for yourself</h3>
<p>The general population absolutely has no interest in poetry, and you can demonstrate that for yourself with a micro qualitative study. If you’re a poet, ask your non-poet friends to name a single living poet who isn’t you. (If you’re one of my friends reading this, name a living poet who isn’t me.)</p>

<p>After they all say “Amanda Gorman”, ask if they could have named one on January 19.</p>

<p>I don’t mean to diminish Gorman’s moment or her impact—occasional poems are so hard, and she nailed it, and connected emotionally &amp; intellectually with a ton of people—but as I mentioned <a href="/howOurStudentsLearned">in a recent post</a>, Presidential inaugurations &amp; weddings are two of the only places non-poets <em>might</em> encounter poetry organically (versus the inescapability of, say, a new Taylor Swift single).</p>

<p>How many non-poets do you know who search out poetry, who read it more often than when a poem/poet goes viral? Amanda Gorman was incidental for most people; few to zero people tuned in to see her. I—a reasonably active participant in literary spaces—didn’t even know Biden was going to have a poet.</p>

<h3 id="unidentified-mystery-man">“Unidentified mystery man”</h3>
<p>In June 2021, Page Six (a New York Post holding) published <a href="https://pagesix.com/2021/06/15/padma-lakshmi-kisses-mystery-man-after-adam-dell-split/" rel="nofollow">this article</a> about Padma Lakshmi on a date with an “unidentified mystery man”.</p>

<p>Reader, that man was Terrance Hayes. Here’s a partial list of Hayes’s accomplishments:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Guggenheim fellow</li>
  <li>MacArthur fellow</li>
  <li>National Book Award winner (<em>Lighthead</em>)</li>
  <li><em>New York Times</em> poetry editor (2017–2018)</li>
</ul>

<p>Also he’s tall, extremely handsome, &amp; an engaging reader at his events. In other words, he’s one of the most talented, accomplished, visible, &amp; marketable poets to ever live.</p>

<!-- Terrance Hayes screenshot -->
<figure>
<img class="docimage" src="images/terrance-hayes.png" alt="Poet &amp; handsome guy, Terrance Hayes" style="max-width: 100%" />   <figcaption style="max-width: 100%">
Some guy the <em>Top Chef</em> host kissed
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>To be fair, other publications picked up the story and performed the basic journalistic work of discovering the name of the only other person in the story. But it speaks volumes about poetry’s role in America that one of the most decorated poets was a non-entity to this pop culture pub.</p>

<h3 id="dont-read-the-comments">Don’t read the comments</h3>
<p>One thing I noticed about the fallout was how much some poets need to believe that poetry is this force in the world. I love poetry. It means more to me than I can articulate. And I think it’s uniquely suited to approach &amp; comment on certain things in certain ways; as Edward Hirsch says, poetry is really hard, but there must be something vital about it, some reason we keep doing it—some reason every culture ever has had poetry.</p>

<p>But that doesn’t mean most (or even many) people care about poetry. It doesn’t mean poetry is capable of saving the world from anything. I think this is the “toxic positivity” Rose was referring to. So many people jumped into the comments to say something like “I’ve taught poetry to my students for 20 years and seen it effect hundreds of powerful reactions”. That’s truly wonderful. Not a response to what she tweeted, but wonderful that you’ve made that impact. How many of the students who had those powerful experiences do you honestly believe read another poem after your class?</p>

<p>If you’re a poet who’s still on the fence, ask yourself this—how many of your non-poet friends have:</p>
<ul>
  <li>attended any of your readings?</li>
  <li>bought any your books?</li>
  <li>asked to read one of your poems?</li>
  <li>ever asked you how your writing is going?</li>
</ul>

<p>If non-poets cared about poetry, surely the ones who love poets would, at the very least, occasionally ask about their practice—this practice they love that’s a fundamental part of their lives and, I’m supposed to believe, a universal balm.</p>

<p>Poetry may have saved your life (like in some ways it did mine), but I don’t need to believe this art has a mythical power for it to be a force in my life. I’m grateful for the personal, private ways poetry has devastated me and then put me back together. That I occasionally share those experiences with a small community of other writers, or even more rarely the world at large, deepens my love for poetry, but is not essential.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew P. Dillon</name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="poetryWorld" /><category term="techJourney" /><category term="tgp" /><category term="troubleshooting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Poetry Twitter blew up this month, and I’ve got cold takes.]]></summary></entry></feed>